What if this was your house? Power's out. Lights are dead.
假設這是你的家 突然斷電 一片漆黑
Your little ones in their bunk bed down the hall, crying out...
你的小傢伙們被困在走廊盡頭的雙層床上 哭著大喊…
Mommy! Daddy! Come quick! I'm scared!
媽媽！爸爸！快來！我害怕！
- You need to get there, and fast. - Coming, honey! Daddy's coming!
- 你必須第一時間趕過去 - 來了寶貝！爸爸來了！
You'll need a weapon. But first, you'll need a flashlight.
你需要一件防身的傢伙 但首先 你需要的是一個手電筒
But you're in the dark! What are you gonna do?
但你四週一片漆黑 你該怎麼辦？
How are you gonna find it? I'll tell you how.
要怎麼找到手電筒？ 讓我來告訴你答案
The Glow-in-the-Dark Flashlight!
夜光手電筒！
That's right, folks! I'm Larry Daley of Daley Devices,
沒錯 朋友們！ 我是戴利設備的拉瑞·戴利
and we're gonna spend the next paid-programing block
接下去的電視導購單元
rocking your world.
將令您終身難忘
And I brought along a friend to do it.
和我一起來的還有我的朋友
George Foreman, ladies and gentlemen!
女士們先生們 歡迎喬治·福爾曼
Fantastic, Larry, fantastic! Isn't he fantastic, America?
棒極了 拉瑞 棒極了！ 大家說他是不是很棒
But, seriously, isn't it true that just two years ago,
不過說真的 這一切都是真的嗎 僅僅兩年以前
you were working as a night guard at some dusty museum?
你還只是一名博物館夜班守衛
That is true, two-time world heavyweight champ George Foreman.
沒錯 你是連續兩屆世界重量級拳王 喬治·福爾曼
I was just a regular Joe with a flashlight and a dream.
而我只是一個小人物喬 拿著夜光手電筒懷揣著一個夢
You mean a regular Larry.
應該是小人物拉瑞
But what's no joke is you're CEO of Daley Devices,
但這不是開玩笑 如今你是戴利設備的首席執行官
creator of such indispensable items as the Super Big Dog Bone!
你的發明已經成了我們生活的必備品 比如超級大狗骨頭！
- You like that one? - The Unlosable Key Ring!
- 你們喜歡嗎？ - 還有防丟失鑰匙圈！
Oh, yeah, that little chestnut!
哦 對 那個小栗子
And now your latest breakthrough... Say it with me, America!
而現在你又推出了最新發明 大家一起說！
The Glow-in-the-Dark Flashlight!
夜光手電筒！
Whatever the household crisis, this is Daley Devices. Can I help you?
家庭安防有保障 這堿O戴利設備 有什麼可以幫助您？
Tina, give this back to Stewart. I don't trust his math, okay?
蒂娜 把這份文件還給斯圖爾特 他的計算能力糟透了
- That guy called again. - Again?
- 那傢伙又打來了 - 又打來？
Lar! Huge news! We got the Wal-Mart meeting.
拉瑞！爆炸新聞！沃爾瑪同意和我們洽談了
- No! When? - Yeah. Three days.
- 不會吧！什麼時候？ - 三天後
Okay, all right. We got a lot of work to do.
好吧 好的 那我們有的好準備了
Well, okay, did you just hear me say "Wal" and "Mart" together?
你有聽我說嗎？那可是沃爾瑪
Yeah! I know, it's huge.
是！我知道 這是件大事！
So just take a second to be happy about it.
那該慶賀一下啊
All right.
好吧
You're totally making fun of me.
你真是太掃興了
No, let's hold off on the victory parade till we close, okay?
今天全公司集體慶祝直到關門 怎麼樣？
You got it.
遵命
- And when does he want to meet? - They want Friday morning, 10:00 a.m.
- 他想約什麼時候見面？ - 禮拜五早上十點
Okay, then, you know what? Cancel that pitch
好吧 你知道該怎麼做 取消推廣會
for the electric saw thing with the propeller, all right?
關於螺旋推進電鋸的那個 好嗎？
- I just want to focus on this. - Okay.
- 我得集中思想 - 好的
- Just this. - My daughter's birthday, canceled!
- 就這樣 - 我女兒的生日也泡湯了！
You can go home. I'm gonna be pretty late, okay.
你可以先回去 我會呆到很晚 好嗎？
Okay, boss.
是 老闆
Hello! Excuse me! Unauthorized personnel!
嗨抱歉 未經許可不得入內！
If it isn't our very own Mr. Success Story.
這不是我們的一夜成名先生嗎
Come for one of your nostalgia tours? I haven't seen you for a few months.
來重遊故地嗎？ 好幾個月沒看到你了
Yeah, I've been busy. What's going on here?
對 我一直很忙 這堳蝏穧^事？
Progress, so they tell me.
發展 他們這樣告訴我的
The future. Behold, Natural History, version 2.0.
這是發展趨勢 自然歷史博物館 2.0版
Welcome to The Museum of Natural History, where history comes to life!
歡迎來到自然歷史博物館 這堹酮搢麭斨A活的歷史！
Step up, ask your question.
站出來 問出你的問題
Then let the next little boy or girl have their turn.
孩子們排好隊一個一個來
Okay, where were you born?
好吧 你的出生地？
Right here in New York City, on Twentieth Street.
就在這 紐約市 二十大街
October 27th, the year of our Lord 1858.
我生於1858年10月27日
Blah, blah, blah. History, history. Learning, learning.
歷史 歷史 學習 學習
Changing America, one child at a time.
改變美國人民 一次一個孩子提問
That's great. So you're adding some new interactive exhibits?
很棒 這麼說你們打算增加一些這樣的互動展品？
No, Mr. Daley, not adding. Replacing the old exhibits.
不 戴利先生 不是增加 而是替換所有舊的展品
- Where are they going? - Away.
- 那舊展品放去哪堙H - 清理出去
We're getting rid of all this junk. The dioramas, the waxworks,
這些垃圾都要被清走 模型 蠟像
even some of the shabbier animals, like this scrawny little monkey.
還有這些破爛的動物模型 比如這隻手骨嶙峋的猴子
You should be careful. He's a capuchin.
你手腳輕點 它是只僧帽猴
It's a monkey.
它是個猴子
He's a rare breed. He's a capuchin. He's not just a monkey.
它是稀有品種 它叫僧帽猴 不是只普通猴子
"Monkey", then. I said "monkey". Why be specific?
猴子 它就叫猴子 幹嘛分的這麼細？
When you're throwing away a monkey, you don't need the Latin name.
當你準備扔掉一隻猴子時 你不需要為它取個拉丁名吧
Are you throwing him away or are you moving him?
你到底是扔掉它還是搬到別的地方？
What are you, the Primate Garbage Police? Let it go, baby.
你專管靈長垃圾嗎？ 算了吧 寶貝
- Whose idea was this? - Me, of course.
- 這是誰的主意？ - 當然是我的
I'm in charge. Me and the board.
這事我說了算 我和董事會
Mainly the board.
主要是董事會的意見
Anyway, why do you care?
你管這麼多幹嘛？
No, it's just that people love this stuff.
不是 人們愛這些展品
People, Mr. Daley, love "What's next?"
人們 戴利先生 永遠喜新厭舊
You should know that. You left.
這你應該清楚 你不是也走了
My situation changed. My business took off...
我的情況不一樣 我的生意剛剛起步
Yeah, you became a success. So would I, if I was a night guard.
對 你成功了 如果我是夜班守衛 我也能
So where are these guys going?
那這些會被運到哪堙H
Deep storage. Federal Archives.
聯邦檔案館的地下儲藏室
- Where's that? - Washington, D.C.
- 在哪兒？ - 華盛頓
The Smithsonian.
史密森尼學會
There's got to be something that we can do.
我們可以阻止他們的
It's done! They leave tomorrow morning. It's over.
沒用了！它們明天早上就會被運走 都結束了！
Hey, buddy, how you doing? How you doing with all this?
嗨 夥計 你好嗎？ 你這把老骨頭還好嗎？
You want what's in here?
想看看我給你帶什麼了？
You think I got something for you? You think I got a little rope?
猜猜我給你帶什麼？ 是一條繩子嗎？
Think you're stronger than me, huh?
你扯得過我嗎？
Is that all you got, huh?
你就這點力氣嗎？
Lawrence! Good to see you, lad!
勞倫斯！很高興見到你 孩子
Yeah, you too, Teddy.
我也是 泰德！
The Guardian of Brooklyn has returned!
布魯克林的守護者回來了！
Hey, Ahk. Look, McPhee told me what's going on around here.
嘿 阿克 聽著 麥克菲都告訴我了
- I had no idea. - Indeed.
- 我有個主意 - 真的
A lot has transpired, Lawrence, since your last visit.
勞倫斯 你最後一次來這兒以後 發生了很多事
One would say that...
俗話說…
- Just... - Cricket.
- 稍等 - 忙人
Hey, Bocephus! Little help over here!
嘿 誰來幫把手！
Hey.
嘿
Hey, fellas. How you doing?
嘿 夥計們 你們好嗎？
Well, lookee here.
看看
If it ain't Mr. Big-in-the-Britches himself,
大人物親自來啦
come back just in time to see us off!
你正好趕上見我們最後一面
Yeah, Jed, I heard. Look, I don't even know how this happened.
傑德 我聽說了 聽著 我真的不知道事情會變成這樣
Yeah. Yeah, real mystery how this happened.
是啊 你當然會覺得很奇怪
Maybe the answer's on that magic buzzing box there in your hand!
也許答案就在你手堥滬 嗡嗡作響的盒子
You weren't here, Gigantor! That's how it happened!
你不在這堣F 鐵人 所以事情才會變成這樣！
Ain't no mystery!
沒什麼可奇怪的！
The fact is, Larry, there's no one else here to speak on our behalf
事實是 拉瑞 他們開會的時候
during business hours.
沒人再為我們說話了
None, none, dum-dum.
沒人 沒人 笨瓜 笨瓜
Hey, guys! It's okay!
嘿 夥計們！沒事的
I'll call the board in the morning, all right? I got some pull now.
我明天一早就給董事會打電話好嗎？ 我會做彌補
I'll handle this. We're gonna be okay here.
我會處理好 我們都會沒事
"We"? Did you hear that? You hear Daydream Johnny?
我們？你聽見了嗎？ 還是我們在做白日夢 強尼？
There ain't been a "we" ever since you put us on the "pay no mind" list.
自從你對我們撒手不管以後 你是你 我們是我們
And that's a cold place to be, boy.
這真讓人心寒
Larry, what's done is done.
拉瑞 悲劇已經發生
Even the glory of Rome had to come to an end.
即使輝煌的羅馬帝國也有滅亡的一天
Would you please not look dramatically off into the middle distance
你能不能別用這種悲哀的眼神看著空氣
when you say that? It makes me feel worse.
你這麼說 讓我更加痛苦
I don't know what you're talking about.
我不知道你在說些什麼
Where are you looking? Where are you looking? I'm over here.
你看什麼？你看什麼？ 我在這
Just a bit of wall.
我只是在看著牆
Look, guys, maybe it won't be so bad.
聽著夥計們 也許事情沒那麼糟
Yes, you make a good point.
對 你說的對
But this is the Smithsonian we're talking about here.
我們只是要去史密森尼而已
Dexter, you don't know that.
德克斯特 你根本不懂
You're missing the point, Gigantor! They're shipping us out!
重點不是這個 鐵人 我們要被掃地出門了！
Larry, I know you're trying to make us feel better.
拉瑞 我知道你只是在安慰我們
I can see that you're genuinely slightly bothered,
我能看得出你在真誠的為我們著急
but it's never going to be the same.
但今天也許是最後一次了
All of us here, together, in this place.
我們所有人 聚在一起 在這
It ain't never gonna be home, boy.
這埵A也不是家了
Jedediah, please! Lawrence,
傑迪戴亞 別這樣 勞倫斯
these are emotional times for all of us.
這種情況下大家都容易激動
But it is our last night as a family,
但這是我們作為一家人的最後一夜
and I don't want to see it squandered in self-pity.
我不願意看著你們浪費時間自怨自艾
So who will join me for one final stroll through these hallowed halls?
讓我們在這神聖大殿做最後一次遊行吧 誰願意來？
- Do you want to go for a walk? - No.
- 你想去逛一圈嗎？ - 不
I'm just gonna squander it in self-pity.
我只想自怨自艾
My dear, shall we?
親愛的 上馬吧
Safe journey, my love.
一路平安 親愛的
Hey, Dexter, want some help there?
嘿 德克斯特 要幫忙嗎？
Hey, come on, man. No hard feelings, all right?
別這樣夥計 別鬧情緒好嗎？
It's gonna be fine.
都會過去的
It's almost dawn, Lawrence.
天快亮了 勞倫斯
Yeah. So, where's your crate, Teddy?
是啊 那麼 你的木箱呢 泰德？
I won't be making this journey, Lawrence.
我不和他們一起走 勞倫斯
It seems myself, Rexy, and a few of the signature exhibits
我 雷克斯 還有其他一些簽名展品
will be staying here for now.
還要留下 暫時
Without the tablet?
可是復活金牌不在了
In truth, Lawrence,
事實上 勞倫斯
Ahkmenrah's tablet will be remaining here with him.
阿卡曼拉的復活金牌 會和他一起留在這
What?
什麼？
They're going without the tablet, my friend.
復活金牌不能隨他們一起走了 我的朋友
I'm afraid this night is their last.
這恐怕是他們的最後一夜了
You didn't tell them.
你沒告訴他們
Sometimes it's more noble to tell a small lie than deliver a painful truth.
作為一個紳士 痛苦我們只會留給自己
- Are you gonna be okay? - I shall do my best.
- 你會沒事吧？ - 我會盡力
And who knows?
誰知道呢？
Sometimes the greatest change brings about even greater opportunity.
俗話說 塞翁失馬焉知非福
Look at you, Lawrence.
看看你 勞倫斯
You left this place and created quite a life for yourself.
你離開之後 生活發生了翻天覆地的變化
Yeah, I guess so.
是啊 也許你說的對
I should hope you'd do more than guess, my friend.
我的朋友 你要對自己有信心
You're a captain of industry. The world at your fingertips.
你是大企業的老闆 一手掌握大權
It seems to me you have everything you wanted.
在我看來 你擁有了一切你想要的
Yeah, no, I know.
沒有 我自己知道
No, you don't. If I may, lad,
不 你不懂 如果可以 孩子
allow me to offer you one piece of advice.
請允許我給你一點建議
The key to happiness, to true happiness, is...
獲得真正幸福的關鍵是…
Hang on one sec. I just gotta...
稍等一下 我得…
I got this Japanese deal.
處理一下這宗和日本人的買賣
No, okay, I'm turning this off. I'm sorry.
哦 算了 我關機吧 對不起
The key to happiness?
幸福的關鍵是？
I'll see you, Teddy.
再見 泰德
So they're gone? There's nothing you can do?
他們真的走了？ 你什麼忙都沒幫上？
I wish there was, man. I'm telling you, I tried everything.
我也想做點什麼夥計 告訴你 我已經竭盡所能了
I talked to McPhee, I called the board,
我和麥克菲談了 給董事會打了電話
but they shipped them out this morning.
但今天早上他們還是被運走了
This is a lot of food, Dad.
好多吃的啊 老爸
Yeah. Ed from work's gonna come by. I thought I told you.
對 我公司的愛德今天要過來 我記得我告訴過你
We just have to go over a couple of little work things.
我們要討論一些工作上的事情
- So you're working tonight. - I used to work every night, remember?
- 那今晚你要工作？ - 以前我每晚都工作 記得嗎？
That was when you had the coolest job in the world.
那時你擁有全世界最酷的工作
Yeah, well, "cool" doesn't pay for your Guitar God VI or whatever.
但是「酷」可支付不起你昂貴的吉他 和別的花銷
- Hello? - Gigantor! It's me, Jedediah!
- 喂？ - 鐵人！是我 傑迪戴亞
- Hold! Hold! - Jed?
- 撐住！撐住！ - 傑德?
Never surrender!
決不投降！
Jed, what are you... How did you dial the phone?
傑德 你們在幹嘛？ 你是怎麼撥通電話的？
Long story! That brazen little monkey stole the tablet,
說來話長 那個死猴子偷來了復活金牌
and now we're in a world of hurt, boy!
我們這堻ㄔ揭角@片了老兄！
- What's going on? - Kahmunrah!
- 出什麼事了？ - 卡門拉！
- Kahmunrah? - Ahkmenrah's big brother! He's here!
- 卡門拉？ - 阿卡曼拉的哥哥 他來了！
- And trust me, not a friendly! - Never!
- 相信我 他是來者不善！ - 決不！
I repeat, not a friendly!
我重複一遍 來者不善！
- Is that Attila, Jed? - I don't know how much longer
- 那是匈奴王的聲音嗎 傑德？ - 我不知道我們還能撐多久
- we can fight them off! No! - Jed? Are you okay?
- 不要！ - 傑德？你沒事吧？
- Let go of me! Help! - Hey, Jed.
- 放開我！救命！ - 嘿 傑德
- Let go! No, you let go of me! Help! - Jed?
- 放開我 放開 你放開我 救命啊！ - 傑德
What was that about?
怎麼了？
I don't know.
我不知道
Here, come on. Gonna drop you off at your mom's.
快點 我要把你送到你媽那兒
- What's going on, Dad? - I'm gonna go find out.
- 出什麼事了 老爸？ - 我會去弄清楚的
Okay, buddy, McPhee said the Federal Archives are in the Smithsonian.
夥計 麥克菲說聯邦檔案館在史密森尼
Where exactly am I going?
那我究竟要去哪塈銦H
That's the thing, Dad. The Smithsonian is actually 19 different museums.
問得好 老爸 史密森尼其實是19座不同的博物館
They're laid out around the National Mall,
它們圍繞著國家廣場
from the Capitol to the Lincoln Memorial.
從國會大廈一直到林肯紀念碑
They got everything there. There's actually some really cool stuff.
那堶惜偵臕禱~都有 確實有很多特別酷的東西
Nicky, please focus. Which museum are the Archives in?
尼基 別扯別的 檔案館到底在哪座博物館
Not in, under.
不是博物館 而是地下
It looks like it runs underneath the entire Smithsonian.
從這堿搘戌據了整個史密森尼的地下空間
So if Ahkmenrah's tablet is down there...
那麼如果阿卡曼拉的復活金牌在那下面的話
The biggest museum in the world is coming alive.
所有歷史人物都將重見天日
What is exactly is your plan here, Dad?
你打算怎麼辦 老爸？
- Don't worry about it. - You have no plan, do you?
- 這你別擔心 - 你根本沒有計劃是不是？
Now, Nicholas, I have a very good, highly thought-out plan.
尼古拉斯 我有一個超級絕妙的計劃
- You have no plan. - Yes, I have no plan.
- 你沒有計劃 - 好吧 我沒有計劃
I'll call you when I'm in.
我進去後再聯絡
Here you go. Thanks.
給你 謝謝
Welcome to the biggest museum in the world.
歡迎來到全世界最大的博物館
I know, right? It's a trip.
是啊 這像一場旅行
How about these planes dangling from the ceilings, huh? Pretty weird.
那些掛在天花板上的飛機怎麼樣？ 很神奇吧
Hi, excuse me. Could you tell me how to get to the Federal Archives?
不好意思打擾了 請問聯邦檔案館怎麼去？
Of course. Just be a historical document worthy of storing for all eternity.
如果你是一個有永久保存價值的檔案 就能進去了
I'm kidding. He's not a document.
開個玩笑 他不是檔案
I'm sorry, sir, the Archives are underground, and they're a secure area.
抱歉 先生 檔案館在地下層 那堿O禁區
Really? Like, totally secure? Okay, thank you.
真的？完全禁止入內嗎？ 好吧 謝謝
Ladies and gentlemen, the museum will be closing in one hour.
女士們先生們 博物館將在一小時後閉館
Kahmunrah.
卡門拉
Hey! What are you doing?
嘿 你想幹嘛？
- No touching. - No, I wasn't gonna touch it.
- 嚴禁觸摸 - 不 我沒有想摸
You're moving in with some I.T.T., bro.
你已經產生「摸機」了 夥計
- I.T. T? - That's "Intent to Touch", homey.
- 摸機？ - 觸摸動機 朋友
No, I wasn't. You're not allowed to go over the...
我沒有 我知道這不許碰…
- What, are you gonna kiss it? - All right, sorry.
- 怎麼 你還想親它嗎？ - 好吧 對不起
Put your hand on it and touch it. 'Cause I stand there
你手放上去碰一下試試 我站在那兒等上一天
and I wait all day for a little girl like you to come in
就是等像你這樣想摸它的小女孩
and put her precious nail-polished nails all over the exhibits.
用她帶著光鮮亮麗指甲的手碰展品
Sorry. Last time I checked, I thought we lived in a free country, so...
對不起 我以為我們生活在一個自由民主的國家…
- No, we don't. - No?
- 不 不是 - 不是？
It's the United States of Don't Touch That Thing Right in Front of You.
這個國家規定你 不許碰你前面的這個東西
I just want to... I'm allowed to look at it here, okay?
我只是想… 在這兒站著看不犯法吧？
See what happens when you touch it!
你碰一下試試！
So you're threatening me? You're threatening me, Brandon?
你在威脅我嗎？ 你在威脅我嗎 布蘭頓
- It's "Brundon." - Excuse me?
- 是布倫頓 - 什麼？
- "Brundon"! - "Brundon"?
- 布倫頓 - 布倫頓？
- "Brundon." - "Brundon."
- 布倫頓 - 布倫頓
What, did they run out of U's on your nameplate maker?
好像印你的胸卡時他們丟了個字母
I don't know, did they run out of jokes
不知道 你媽是不是沒教過你
at the interesting-joke store that you shop at?
什麼時候該開玩笑？
Sorry, it looks like "Brandon", but...
不好意思 看上去像是布蘭頓…
I'm not here to be your speech therapist. It's "Brundon"!
我不是來教你語音的 是布倫頓
- "Brundon." Okay... - You never heard of the name before?
- 布倫頓 好的… - 你以前沒聽說過這名字嗎？
"Brundon"? No.
布倫頓？沒有
Look up most popular baby names in 1984. "Brundon."
1984年最流行的名字 布倫頓
Okay. Are you threatening me, Brundon?
好吧 你在威脅我嗎 布倫頓？
I don't know, Princess Jasmine. Am I?
我不知道 茉莉公主 我有嗎？
- Oh, wow. Lunabeam nine-volt. - Yeah.
- 哇 月光九號手電筒 - 沒錯
Wonderful piece of hardware, huh?
硬體不錯啊
- That's their title, Lunabeam Nine. - Great.
- 商標在這兒 月光九號 - 太好了
I prefer the Maglite LED myself, but that's just me.
我個人更偏愛美光手電筒
- Do me a huge favor. - What?
- 幫我個大忙 - 什麼忙？
Shove your hands into your pockets, put your attitude way down,
把手放回褲帶 放低你的姿態
and, also, be nice to people.
還有 對人友好些
Great. But could I just ask you one thing?
我能再問你一個問題嗎？
- Yeah. - Okay, so just to be clear,
- 可以 - 我只想弄清楚
- so, I can't do this, right? - Okay, that's actually crazy.
- 我不能碰它 對嗎？ - 好吧 你這個瘋子
Did you just make a decision to possibly end your life
你想找死嗎？
earlier than you were expecting?
你活得不耐煩了吧？
I'm gonna hit you with the flashlight.
我會用手電筒打你
- Now you are threatening me. Okay. - Do not touch it!
- 你在威脅我 - 別碰它！
- Don't touch me. - Do not touch it!
- 別碰我！ - 你別碰它！
- Do not touch it! - Don't touch me!
- 別碰它！ - 你別碰我！
I'll touch you with my flashlight all day.
我想怎麼碰你就怎麼碰你
No, your flashlight is meant to illuminate.
不 你的手電筒是用來照明的
I will literally rent a camper,
我打個比方 我們去露營
and we will drive across America with my flashlight on your chest.
開著車橫跨美國 一路上我都要拿手電筒碰你
- Don't do that. - Don't do what?
- 你別這樣 - 別怎樣？
Want to see what happens when I do it one more time?
我就碰了你了怎麼樣？
- Let's see what happens. - Watch you do nothing.
- 你等著瞧 - 瞧什麼瞧
Let's watch you do nothing when I do this.
瞧你傻站在那兒嗎
Seriously, Brandon...
說真的 布蘭頓…
- Brundon. - Brundon,
- 布倫頓 - 布倫頓
you do not know who you're dealing with.
你知道我是誰嗎？
You think you know what it means to be a guard, huh?
你知道當守衛意味著什麼嗎？
Trust me, you don't know the meaning of the word.
相信我 你根本不懂守衛的含義
I have seen things that you could not imagine.
我見過的東西你連想都不敢想
- Like what kind of stuff? - I'm not gonna tell you.
- 比如什麼？ - 我不會告訴你
- But you're gonna drop the flashlight... - The way you said it,
- 但是你得放下手電筒… - 你這麼說
it sounded like you were gonna say something cool.
聽上去你有什麼很有意思的事
Yeah, well, you don't get to hear it.
對 可惜你聽不到
Drop the flashlight.
放下手電筒
We cool?
沒事了吧？
That's actually pretty cool, what you just did.
你剛才真是太酷了
Thank you.
謝謝
No hard feelings?
別記恨我好嗎?
- All right? Sorry. - Okay.
- 好嗎？對不起 - 沒事
- I'm sorry. - No, It's my fault. I shouldn't have...
- 我很抱歉 - 不 是我的錯 我不應該…
No. It takes two opposing forces to cause friction, and...
不 一個巴掌拍不響 再說…
And you're just doing your job, all right.
你只是在盡你的本職 沒事的
- Take it easy, man. - Yeah!
- 放鬆點 夥計 - 好的！
That guy's great.
那傢伙真酷
Okay, buddy, I'm in.
好了 夥計 我進去了
Great. Where are you?
太棒了 告訴我你現在的位置
The northeast corridor of the Castle, just off the Commons.
城堡的東北角走廊 剛出國會
- I need you to talk me to the Archives. - Okay.
- 帶我到檔案館 - 好的
At the end of the hall, turn right,
到走廊盡頭 右轉
and there should be a stairwell coming up on your left.
在你左手邊可以看到一個樓梯間
- Got it. - Now, it's kind of a maze down there.
- 明白 - 這下面像個迷宮
Those underground tunnels connect a bunch of different buildings.
地下通道把不同建築連成一體
- It could get complicated. - We'd better hurry,
- 地形非常複雜 - 我們沒時間了
we only got 28 minutes till sundown.
還有28分鐘太陽就落山了
When you get down to B level, you want to take another left...
下到B層以後 再一次左轉
- Nick? Hello? Nick? - Dad! Can you hear...
- 尼克 喂 尼克？ - 老爸！聽得見嗎…
Nick, you're... Nick!
尼克 你說…尼克？
- ID, Brundon. - Hey.
- 身份 布倫頓 - 嘿
- Later, dude. - All right. Yeah.
- 你晚了 老兄 - 是啊
All right. Where are you guys?
好了 大夥兒都在哪兒？
Oh, my God.
哦 上帝
You little troublemaker. I'm gonna deal with you later.
你這個搗蛋鬼 我一會兒再找你算賬
No. No! No, no, no!
不 不 不 不 不！
No, English. English, perhaps.
英語 英語會說嗎？
I'm sorry, who are you?
抱歉 你是誰？
I am Kahmunrah, the great king of the great kings,
我是卡門拉 我是王中之王
and from the darkest depths of ancient history,
從最黑暗的古老歷史深處
I have come back to life!
我死而復生！
Perhaps you did not hear what I just said.
你大概沒聽清我的話
I am a centuries-old Egyptian Pharaoh. I was dead,
我是古老埃及的法老 我曾經死去
but now I have come back to life!
但是現在 我死而復生！
Yeah, no. I heard that. I got that. Welcome back.
哦 是 我聽清了 我明白你的意思 歡迎回來！
- Who are you? - Larry Daley. Daley Devices?
- 你是誰？ - 戴利設備的拉瑞·戴利
It's up in New York. It's funny, I know your brother, Ahkmenrah.
我公司在紐約市 很有趣 我還認識你弟弟阿卡曼拉
- Do you? - Yeah.
- 是嗎？ - 是的
He knows baby brother. The favorite son.
他說他認識我弟弟 最受寵的兒子
- Yeah, good kid. - Isn't he just?
- 對 是個好孩子 - 誰說不是呢？
You know, Mother and Father always gave him the best of everything,
知道嗎 媽媽和爸爸總是把所有最好的給他
and I do mean everything. They even gave him the throne.
我說的是所有 甚至包括王位
The throne which was rightfully mine!
我才應該是王位繼承人！
- He never mentioned that. - I'll just bet he didn't.
- 他沒提過這事 - 我打賭他不會說
Well, now begins the era of Kahmunrah, because I have come back to...
不過卡門拉時代現在來臨了 因為我死而復…
Never mind, just hand me the tablet.
算了 把金牌給我
- Don't give it to him, Gigantor! - Keep him away!
別給他 鐵人！
Silence! Silence in there, please!
安靜！你們給我安靜！
- Don't make me come in there! - No! I won't be muzzled!
- 別逼我進去！ - 我不會保持沉默！
Look, that tablet is more powerful
聽著 這金牌所擁有的力量
than you, Larry Daley of Daley Devices, can possibly imagine.
是你這個戴利設備的拉瑞·戴利 根本無法想像的
Bringing things back to life is just a parlor trick.
恢復生命只是其中一個小把戲
With it, I shall unlock the Gate to the Underworld
有了它 我就可以開啟塵封的地下世界之門
and bring forth my army from the Land of the Dead.
從死亡之地召回我的軍隊
So, if it's not too much trouble...
如果不麻煩的話…
...hand it over.
…把它給我
Okay, here you go.
好吧 給你
Wise decision.
明智的選擇
Yeah, I know. I'm sorry, I thought you wanted the Cube, but...
是啊 很抱歉 我以為你是想要那個魔方 不過…
The Cube?
魔方？
The Cube of Rubik.
魔法立方體
All right, what is this Cube of Rubik, then?
好吧 這個魔法立方體是幹什麼的？
The Cube. You know, the one that turns all who oppose you to dust?
就是魔方 那個可以把你的敵人化成灰的魔方
That one? Whatever. I thought...
有這個玩意兒嗎？隨便吧 總之…
It was my bad, 'cause... You know what? By the way,
是我不好 順便說一句
your brother didn't want to mess with it, either.
你弟弟也不想搞得這麼砸
Yeah, he wanted to play it safe, too.
他不想兩敗俱傷
Just, you sort of struck me as a next-level sort of guy, so I was...
只是 你看上去像比他厲害些 所以我…
I am not my brother, Larry.
我不是我弟弟 拉瑞
I will kill you and your friends in the blink of an eye.
只需一眨眼的功夫 我就能殺光你和你的朋友們
Now take me to this Cube of Rubik.
帶我去那個魔法立方體
- Here it is. - Open it.
- 就在這兒 - 打開
Come back here! Come back here with my tablet!
回來！把金牌還給我！
I still have your friends!
你朋友還在我手上！
- Take the wheel! - What?
- 你來開！ - 什麼？
I said, take the wheel! Oh, we're in it now! I love it! I love it!
我說你來開 打起來了 打起來了 我愛它
Just keep her straight, I'll handle the rest.
筆直往前 其他我來對付
Now, charge!
前進！
Okay, so what's the plan here?
好吧 接下去你有什麼計劃？
We're Americans! We don't plan, we do!
我們是美國人！我們從不計劃 我們是行動家！
Now hold on!
不要減速！
See that? Act first, think later! Works every time!
看到沒有？先行而後思 每次都管用！
You're in good hands!
我可是好手！
General George A. Custer of the Fighting U.S. 7th Cavalry,
美國第七騎兵隊將軍 喬治·阿姆斯特朗·卡斯特
at your service.
為您效勞
I'm good, I'm good! Fly, you fool!
我沒事 繼續開 笨蛋
What's the rumpus, ace?
你們吵什麼吵 牛仔？
Look, lady, could you get out of the way?
聽著 女士 你能讓開嗎？
Lady? Who are you calling lady? The name is Amelia.
女士？你叫誰女士？ 我是阿梅莉亞
Amelia Earhart! Perhaps you've heard of me?
阿梅莉亞·埃爾哈特 我想你聽說過我吧
Oh, right. You're a famous pilot or whatever.
哦 是啊 著名飛行員什麼的吧
Pilot? I was the first woman to fly the Atlantic!
飛行員？ 我可是第一個飛越大西洋的女性
First woman to receive the Flying Cross,
第一個榮獲飛行十字勳章的女性
first woman to fly across the 48 states in a gyroprop.
第一個駕駛自轉旋翼機 飛越美國48個州的女飛行員
Now if you'd wipe that perhaps-permanent look of alarm off your kisser,
如果你願意的話請先放下你那副永遠緊張兮兮的嘴臉
I was wondering if you might be so kind as to tell me exactly where I am.
請告訴我我現在在哪兒 非常感謝
You're in a museum. Or, actually, under it.
你在一個博物館 準確點是博物館下面
And I'm in kind of a dangerous situation right now,
我現在是眾矢之的
so you might not want to be anywhere near me.
所以你最好躲到離我遠點的地方
- Wow, you're fast. - What's your name, flyboy?
- 你動作真快 - 你叫什麼 飛行員？
My name is Larry Daley.
我叫拉瑞·戴利
Well, Larry Daley, in case you weren't listening,
拉瑞·戴利 你給我聽好了
I'm not one to shy away from danger.
我可不是個膽小怕事的人
How about spears? Are you one to shy away from spears?
那矛呢 你怕不怕矛呢？
Let's ankle, skipper! Now we're gonna have some fun.
讓我們找點樂子 機長！ 痛快玩一場吧
Ninety-eight, ninety-nine, bingo!
98 99 完美
Like a Golden Fleece.
像金羊毛一樣
All right, troops, when your enemies captured me,
聽著 士兵們 當你們的敵人抓住我的時候
they made themselves my enemies as well.
他們也就成了我的甕中之鱉
Big mistake. Big mistake.
大錯誤 一個大錯誤
All right, here's the plan.
我的計劃是這樣的
On the third bugle blast, I shall loudly announce, "Attack!"
吹響三聲號角 我會大聲宣佈：「攻擊！」
At which point, we will all jump out of this box
然後我們全體跳出這個箱子
and attack.
開始攻擊
Mind bomb. What do you think?
很震撼吧 覺得怎麼樣？
You, Sacaja...
你說 薩什麼什麼…
That is not my name.
那不是我的名字
- Sacajamea. - No.
- 薩卡婭米爾 - 不是
- Sack-in-a-box. - No.
- 變態 娘娘腔（俚語） - 不是
Cinco de Mayo.
（西班牙文5月5日 一個節日）
I know you are a famous general...
我知道你是個著名的將軍…
That's all right, that's all right. I'm a person, just like you.
那算不上什麼 我也是個普通人 和你一樣
But won't yelling, "Attack!" Alert the enemy
當你大叫「攻擊」的時候
that we are about to attack?
敵人不就立刻知道我們要攻擊了嗎？
What?
什麼？
Yeah, I guess so.
哦 也許你說的對
You're quite the popular fellow, Mr. Daley.
你很受歡迎嘛 戴利先生
Why don't you just skedaddle?
你幹嘛不直接逃走？
I can't skedaddle. My friends are being held down there.
我不能逃 我的朋友還在他們手上
I got to go get them. I got to find another way down.
我得去救他們 得另找一條路下去
This is new.
以前沒見過
Hey, it's all right. I don't want to hurt you.
沒事 我不會傷害你們
I don't think it's you they're afraid of, Mr. Daley.
我想他們怕的不是你 戴利先生
Trade you. Thanks.
交換 謝謝
Back off! Just back off!
退後 給我退後！
I will fork you!
小心被我叉到
How about you, huh?
別輕舉妄動
Never send a boy to do a woman's job.
男人就是不如女人
I spent two weeks spear-hunting with a tribe in Micronesia.
我曾用兩個星期的時間在密克羅尼西亞群島和土著學習用矛
The Micronesians had much slower reflexes.
密克羅尼西亞人的反應沒這麼快
Come on!
走
It's over! It's over! It's all over!
戰爭結束了！戰爭結束了！
Well, this is one humdinger of a hootenanny.
這兒可真是熱鬧啊
Excuse me. Sorry. Excuse me.
讓一下 不好意思 讓一讓
Wow, four bars in 1945.
哇 1945年的信號這麼強
- Hello? - Dad, finally!
- 喂？ - 老爸 總算通了！
I've been studying these plans to the Archives.
我一直在研究檔案館地形
Looks like once you get down the stairwell...
一旦你下了樓梯…
Oh, I'm way past the stairwell, Nicky.
哦 我早就下了樓梯了 尼基
- So you found everyone? - Sort of.
- 這麼說你找到大家了？ - 算是吧
What is that flibberty-widget you are talking to?
你在對著什麼東西講話？
- Who's that? - It's Amelia Earhart.
- 那是誰？ - 阿梅莉亞·埃爾哈特
You found Amelia Earhart?
你找到了阿梅莉亞·埃爾哈特？
I... Hey!
我…嘿！
- Wait a minute! - Buddy, what's your hurry?
- 等會兒！ - 老兄 你急什麼啊！
Didn't you hear? The war's over!
你沒聽到嗎？戰爭結束啦！
Sorry. These guys are chasing me.
抱歉 那些人在追我
What? What am I looking at, Mardi Gras?
什麼？都是些什麼人啊 狂歡節表演嗎？
- What unit are you from? - I'm from Brooklyn.
- 你是哪堥茠滿H - 布魯克林
What? Are you serious? I'm from Flatbush! Hey, fellas!
你說真的？ 我是弗萊巴許的 嘿 兄弟們
These so-and-so's are trying to rough up my pal here
那些怪人要打我兄弟
just 'cause he's from Brooklyn!
就因為他是布魯克林的
- Thank you! - You got it! Fight!
- 謝謝 - 別客氣 給我打！
Hey, mister! You forgot your...
嘿 先生！你忘了東西…
What the heck is this thing?
這是什麼玩意兒？ （請注意片尾曲中有相關情節）
Excuse me. Mind if I get in here?
對不起 把她借我一會兒行嗎？
Any time you're done, Mr. Daley.
你吻完沒有 戴利先生
- Call me! - Thank you for that.
- 給我打電話！ - 謝謝你
So you're quite the smooth operator, aren't you, Mr. Daley?
你對付女人挺有一套啊 戴利先生
Quick!
快！
- That actually worked. - What's next?
- 終於擋住了 - 接下去幹嘛？
Look, nothing personal, but I'm kind of in the middle of something here
聽著 我不是針對你 不過我現在正處於水深火熱中
that's not really your fight.
這可不是你開飛機這麼簡單
It's because I'm a woman, isn't it?
就因為我是個女人 對不對？
No, it's because I've got this ancient raised-from-the-dead evil Pharaoh guy
不 因為有個死而復生的邪惡法老
who's willing to kill me and probably anyone near me to get this tablet
要我手上這塊石板 他會殺了我甚至我身邊的任何一個人
so he can rule the world.
有了石板他就能統治世界
So it is because I'm a woman!
所以說還是因為我是女人！
- Look, I... - No, you look, Mr. Daley!
- 聽著 我… - 不 你給我聽著 戴利先生！
If it weren't for me, you'd still be lost in that monochromatic mayhem!
要不是我把你拉出來了 你現在還陷在那個黑白鬧劇中
- Lost in what? - Black and white photo, you boob!
- 陷在什麼中？ - 那張黑白照片 蠢貨
Now listen, and listen good. I can help you.
聽著 聽好了 我想幫你
I want to help you, and not because I like you, which so far I don't,
我想幫你 不是因為我喜歡你 我才不喜歡你
but because I smell adventure, and, damn it, I want in.
而是因為我聞到了冒險的味道 見鬼 我要加入你
Okay. Don't blame me if something happens to you.
好吧 出了事可別怪我
I should be so lucky.
我的命長著呢
I am Kahmunrah. I am half god,
我是卡門拉 我是半個神
once removed on my mother's side,
從我出生開始
rightful ruler of Egypt, future ruler of...
我就是埃及王國的合法繼承人 將來也要統治…
Well, everything else.
所有一切
Now, I have lost some men.
我損失了一些人
So, I am in need of some new generals to join me in my little plan
所以現在我需要一些幫手
of conquering this world.
和我一起征服世界
Ivan the Terrible.
恐怖的伊凡
Napoleon Bonaparte.
拿破侖·波拿巴
And young Al Capone.
還有年輕的艾爾·卡彭
Yeah.
是的
Some of the most despicable, most feared leaders in all of history.
你們都是歷史上數一數二的大壞蛋
Gentlemen,
先生們
really, it's just fantastic to meet you all.
真的 我真想不到能見到你們
- And us, too. - And me, you.
- 我們也是 - 我也是
All I ask is your allegiance, and in return, I offer you the world.
只要你們衷心於我 我承諾你們的是整個世界
Literally. Are there any questions?
你們有什麼問題嗎？
Yeah, I got one. How come you're wearing a dress?
我有一個問題 你怎麼會穿著裙子？
This is not a dress. This is a tunic.
這不是裙子 這叫做袍子
It was the height of fashion 3,000 years ago, I assure you.
3000年前很流行的 我告訴你
Are there any other questions?
還有別的問題嗎？
Da. This dress you're wearing,
有 你穿的這個裙子
do we have to wear one of these, too?
我們也要穿嗎？
Were you not listening? I just told Mr. Capone here
你剛才沒在聽嗎？ 我已經回答了卡彭先生的問題
that this is not a dress.
這不是裙子
It is, in fact, a tunic. Very big difference.
事實上 這是件袍子 區別很大的
Are there any other questions?
還有問題嗎？
Any questions not about the dress?
還有別的與裙子無關的問題嗎？
Tunic?
袍子
All right, then. Moonlight is wasting,
那麼好吧 不要浪費月色了
- and the time is short. - Short?
- 我們時間很短 - 短？
Why do you look at me when you say "short"?
為什麼你說「短」的時候要看著我？
Sorry. It slipped out.
對不起 我無意的
Da. If we are talking about world domination,
好吧 如果你說的是征服世界
then of course, I am interested.
那我當然有興趣
But first I want to clarify something so you know what you are getting.
不過我想先澄清一件事情 你得搞清楚你在和誰合作
People always say, "Ivan the Terrible, he's so terrible.
人們總是說：伊凡很恐怖 他很嚇人
"I'm so scared of Ivan. He's bad news."
我很怕伊凡 他是個惡棍
When in fact, the correct translation is
其實正確的翻譯應該是
"Ivan the Awesome".
令人畏懼的伊凡
Ivan the Awesome?
令人畏懼的伊凡？
It's not really as catchy, is it?
那個比較難記 不是嗎？
I mean, "Ivan the Terrible", that really pops.
我是說 恐怖的伊凡更容易記
But I wasn't terrible. In fact, I was quite an effective leader.
可是我一點都不恐怖 事實上我是個很能幹的領袖
Duly noted. Now, I'd like to wrap up the old meet-and-greet
好我記住了 現在我想用一個問題來結束
by asking you gentlemen a question.
今晚的面談會
Are you with me?
你們跟不跟我？
- Yeah. Yeah, sure. - Oui.
- 跟 跟 - 跟
- Da, but... - Then bring Larry Daley of Daley Devices
- 我跟 不過… - 那就把戴利設備的拉瑞·戴利
and the Golden Tablet of Ahkmenrah to me!
還有阿卡曼拉的復活金牌弄來給我！
We'll get you back down to your chums, Mr. Daley.
我帶你下去找你的朋友 戴利先生
You won't get lost following Amelia Earhart.
跟著阿梅莉亞·埃爾哈特 你絕對不會迷路
Quick, get down.
快點 蹲下
Well, well, Mr. Daley, I quite like the way you're holding me.
戴利先生 我很喜歡你這麼摟著我
No. Sorry, I wasn't trying to...
對不起 我不是那個意思…
Oh, please, stop beating your gums, Mr. Daley.
拜託你戴利先生 別嘟嘟囔囔的
You haven't been able to take your cheaters off my chassis
自打你看到我那刻起
since the moment we met.
你的眼睛就沒離開過我的飛機底盤
I literally didn't understand one word of that.
你說的話我全部聽不懂
Is it just me or is there music in the air?
是我聽錯了還是有人在唱歌？
# ... my baby, we can make it shine We can take forever... #
# …寶貝 我們可以使其閃耀 我們能夠保持永遠… #
You! Little flying angel things! Quiet!
你們 會飛的小天使 安靜！
They're cupids, Mr. Daley. Gods of love.
他們是丘比特 戴利先生 是愛神
Great. Gods of love, would you shut up? Please shut up. We're trying to hide.
太棒了 愛神 你們能閉嘴嗎？ 閉嘴 我們會暴露的
# Yeah! More than a woman! Yeah! #
# 耶！特別的女人 耶！#
No, don't change the arrangement, it's not about the arrangement. Quiet!
別換了 不是編曲的問題 給我安靜！
Kick the chorus, y'all!
大家一起唱！
More than a woman
特別的女人
Yo, show me what you got, night guard!
讓我看看你的能耐 守衛！
All right, come on. Let's go.
快點 我們走
# More than a woman to me #
# 對我來說是一個特別的女人 #
# More than a woman #
# 一個特別的女人 #
# She's more than a woman #
# 她是個特別的女人 #
And so, the little tiny man who could not be a smaller or shorter mouse
你這隻小到不能再小的小老鼠
runs into the claws of the giant cat!
自動跑到大貓咪的面前
You're really hung up on the height, aren't you?
你真的這麼在乎高度啊
- No, it's not about height, see... - Yes, you are.
- 我根本不在乎高度… - 不 你在乎
You're saying I'm a little mouse, you're a giant cat.
你的意思是我只是一隻小老鼠 而你是一隻大貓咪
- I am the giant cat. - No offense, I just...
- 我是大貓咪 - 我並不想冒犯你 不過…
You're Napoleon. There's a complex named after you.
你是拿破侖 你擁有很多很多的形容詞
You're famous for being little, and it's true. Look.
矮就是其中之一 真的 你自己看看
Oh, you naive American man-boy.
哦 你這個幼稚的美國男孩
Look. Neither of us are gonna be jamming anytime soon, right?
聽著 現在討論這個很無聊好嗎
So it's not like we should... It's not even an issue.
我們不該浪費時間… 在這個不值一提的問題上
It's not about height or something else. It's a plan. It's a brilliant plan.
人不是以高矮來評價的 是頭腦 一個偉大的頭腦
- So it was a plan. - Snazzy maneuver, Emperor.
- 你是很有頭腦 - 說的好 皇帝先生
Merci, mademoiselle.
謝謝 小姐
Now, if your boyfriend would kindly come with me...
如果你的男朋友能合作點 跟我走…
I'm not her boyfriend.
我不是她男朋友
- Not her boyfriend. - No.
- 不是男朋友 - 不是
Just friends?
普通朋友？
- Yeah, friends. - Acquaintances. Friends.
- 是 普通朋友 - 只是認識而已 普通朋友
Were you guys, like, friends in college
你們的關係 是不是類似那種大學同學
and just afraid now to both ruin your relationship
相互暗戀 想要更進一步發展
by telling the other person that you want to be more than friends,
但卻不敢告訴對方
that you like-like each other?
怕毀了你們現在的關係？
One more time? I'm sorry. I didn't catch the...
再說一遍好嗎 抱歉 我沒聽明白…
Were you guys, like, friends in college
你們的關係 是不是類似那種大學同學
and now both afraid to ruin your relationship
相互暗戀 想更進一步發展
by telling the other person that you want to be more than friends,
但卻不敢告訴對方
that you like-like each other?
怕毀了你們現在的關係？
- No. - No?
- 不是 - 不是？
I just love the nitty-gritty of relationships. All us French do.
我喜歡挖掘兩性關係的本質 這是法國人的愛好
- Great. - Yes. Amour!
- 太好了 - 是啊 愛情
- Now. - Yeah?
行了
- This way, or you die. - Yes.
- 跟我走 要不就殺了你 - 遵命
- Wait, I'm coming with you! - No! Our fight is not with you.
- 等等 我也去 - 不！這事與你無關
...so you gotta bet a second time. - All right. Okay.
…你還得再下一次注 - 好 好吧
My hair is currency in certain parts of Europe.
我的髮型在歐洲一帶流通很廣
It's true. Currency, like gold or paper money.
真的 流通很廣 就像黃金和錢
The Duomo was purchased with just one locket.
一小盒能買下整個大教堂
Listen up, kemosabe.
聽著 朋友
This rodeo clown wouldn't know a flapjack from a flyswatter.
這個馬戲團小丑 連煎餅和蒼蠅拍都分不清
Now, Gigantor's out there risking his hide for us.
現在鐵人正在外面為我們拚命
The least we can do is give him some help.
至少我們要幫他一把
Some big help. But we can't very well do that if we're stuck in here, now, can we?
我們能幫大忙 但是在這塈丰H待斃就什麼忙也幫不上
We need to escape.
我們得逃出去
What's a flapjack?
煎餅是什麼東西？
It's like a biscuit or a scone.
類似一種餅乾或者麵包的東西
- Chest bump? - Yeah.
- 碰胸 - 好的
Then deadly. Watch.
你玩完了 看牌
Guard your cards, okay? Now you bet.
看好你的牌 現在下注吧
Okay, now you got to throw some cards down.
現在你得丟點牌下來
- Ready? - Ready.
- 準備好了？ - 準備好了
Say something. Say anything. This is no fun. You're supposed to...
說點什麼 說點什麼 這不好玩 你必須…
- Hey! What are you two doing out here? - Octavius, go!
- 嘿 你們倆想幹嘛？ - 奧克塔維厄斯 跑！
- You, make a run for it, I'll hold them off! - I will not leave you!
- 你 快跑 我掩護你 - 我不會一個人跑的
Ain't no time for your Roman melodrama! Now, get! Go!
現在不是演羅馬連續劇 快跑 馬上！
Old Jedediah will be fine.
老傑迪戴亞不會有事
Now, you're in real trouble.
好了 你麻煩大了
Why, these aren't real rubies at all.
這些根本不是真的紅寶石
Ruby slippers indeed.
真品紅寶石鞋
But, whoever you are, Archie Bunker,
但是 不管你是誰 Archie Bunker （為美國著名電視劇四海一家的主角）
you had one comfortable throne.
但這椅子坐的可真舒服
Hey, boss.
老大
Caught this one trying to escape through a rust hole in the crate.
這傢伙從箱子的一個蚻}堸k出來 給我們抓住了
One of his little friends got away.
還有一個跑了
Oh, please. What damage could they possibly do?
拜託 他們能幹得了什麼？
Why, they're no bigger than a little grain of couscous. Aren't you?
看看 他們小的好像一粒米 是不是？
You know, two words come to mind when I hear you talk.
聽你說話我想到了兩個詞
"Delusional" and "weirdo".
神經病 精神分裂
And if I had to say a third, "goofy". Just goofy.
如果還要說第三個詞的話 那就是「蠢豬」
Now you let old Jedediah out of here or he's gonna get angry.
你快把老傑迪戴亞放出來 不然他可要發火了
Well played, Jedediah!
說的好 傑迪戴亞
I'm sorry, I can't take you seriously. You're just adorable,
對不起 我實在認真不起來 你太可愛了
even when you're threatening me. It's hilarious.
連你威脅我的樣子也有趣極了
Is it just me, or are these guys unbelievably cute?
是我的問題 還是這些小傢伙真是可愛的要命
Now hold it a second, now.
你給我省省吧
Now, you have a right to keep me as your captive, torture me, even,
你可以囚禁我 甚至折磨我
but don't call me cute! I ain't cute!
但不許說我可愛 我不可愛！
Steady, my friend! Just stay alive! I will find you!
撐住 我的朋友！ 堅持住 我會救你出去！
Gigantor. No!
鐵人 不！
Hello, Mr. Daley. Nice to see you again.
你好 戴利先生 很高興再一次見到你
Now, if you don't mind, I shall take that from you.
如果你不介意的話 這個我要拿走了
Thank you.
謝謝
Finally. Finally! After 3,000 years,
終於！過了整整3000年
my evil army of the damned, my beautiful, beautiful army,
我被詛咒的黑暗軍團 我可愛的軍團
shall be unleashed!
將重見天日！
I'm afraid that Mother and Father may have
我恐怕媽媽和爸爸
slightly changed the combination on me.
背著我稍稍改了一下密碼
I guess this whole unleashing-the-underworld thing
這麼說地下怪物重見天日這套
isn't really working out for you, huh?
行不通了 對吧？
It must be really frustrating, 'cause you've waited thousands of years
你一定很難過吧 畢竟你都等了幾千年了
to come back from the dead and everything,
好不容易死而復生
and now you can't get it open.
卻打不開地獄之門
Fear not, for I shall wait a thousand more if I must.
我不怕 有必要的話我還可以再等上一千年
Good, 'cause in a few hours you'll be standing here in a frustrated position,
很好 不過再過幾個小時你就會 變成一尊沮喪的雕塑
frozen, and I'll walk out of here with my buddies and that'll be that.
凍在那 而我可以帶著我的朋友們 離開這
So, I got all night.
所以 我不介意等上一整晚
Really? All night? Well!
真的嗎？一整晚？
He doesn't.
他等不了
Open that cage.
打開籠子
- What are you doing? - No touching! No touching!
- 你幹嘛？ - 不許碰我！不許碰我！
Don't you manhandle me!
你敢對我動粗試試
- Look, he's having a little tantrum. - Jed?
- 看吶 小傢伙生氣了 - 傑德？
Don't you squirm! Don't squirm. It'll only be worse for you.
別動 別動 不然你會更難受
- Put him down! - Don't be afraid.
- 放開他！ - 別害怕
I shan't hurt you.
我不會傷害你的
I lied.
我騙你了
I don't think he has all night at all, Mr. Daley.
我想他可等不了一整晚 戴利先生
From the looks of things, I'd say he has a little over an hour.
看這速度 他只剩不到一個小時了
Take me out of here!
放我出去！
You were the guardian! You know all about this tablet.
你是守衛！ 你很瞭解這塊復活金牌
You're obviously much more clever than the rest of us.
而你看上去也比我們這堜狾酗H都聰明
You may or may not know the combination,
不管你知道還是不知道密碼
but I am going to give you exactly one hour to figure it out.
我給你一個小時的時間去想
If you do not, I shall kill your friends.
到時間不給我密碼 我就殺光你的朋友
And please don't think about escaping, for I shall be watching you.
還有你別想溜 我會監視你的行動
Look, I don't even know how to begin
聽著 我根本無從下手
to decipher this thing, all right? Really.
我完全不懂怎麼破譯密碼 真的
What a pity.
太可惜了
And your little cowboy friend seemed like such a charming little fellow.
你的牛仔小朋友看上去那麼惹人喜歡
Ah, well. Tick-tock, Mr. Daley. Your hour has begun.
時間在走哦 戴利先生 輪到你行動了
Hey! You got this, partner. I know you do.
我挺你 夥計 我知道你行的
You got this!
我挺你！
There you are! Are you all right? I've been worried sick! Sick I tell you.
你來了！你還好嗎？ 我都快擔心死了！
- No, I'm fine. - So what's our next move, partner?
- 我沒事 - 下一步計劃是什麼 拍檔？
I don't know. I just got to get this tablet translated.
我也不知道 我必須先破譯密碼
Oh, great! This guy again.
哦好極了 又是這傢伙！
Look, buddy, we don't want any trouble, all right?
聽著夥計 我不想惹麻煩好嗎？
Look at that!
看吶
I guess our sassy cephalopod was just a fish
看來冒失的章魚先生僅只是條魚兒
who didn't like being out of water.
它只是不喜歡離開水
He's not such a ballywagger after all.
看上去也沒那麼討厭嘛
Okay. Glad you're happy.
好 知道你很高興
Hello? A little assistance?
喂 幫個忙好嗎？
- Hey, Teddy! Perfect! - Yes!
嘿 泰德 太好了
Maybe you could help us.
也許你能幫我們
I'd love to help you, but first things first.
我很願意幫忙 但先幫我解決我的燃眉之急
My nose is so itchy, it's driving me insane.
鼻子癢的我快瘋掉了
I hate to ask, but, as you see, I'm missing a few body parts.
我知道這很無禮 不過我看上去有點缺胳膊少腿
- Could you please give us a scratch? - Yeah, sure.
- 可以幫我撓一下嗎？ - 當然可以
Oh, yes! That's exquisite. A little over there...
哦 對是這 再過去一點…
- Yes! - More?
- 太棒了！ - 還要？
Oh, yes! Yes! Oh, that's...
哦 是的 是的…
Sweet rutabaga pie, that was divine.
終於舒服了
Theodore Roosevelt, at your service.
西奧多·羅斯福很高興為你效勞
Twenty-sixth President of the United States, Rough Rider,
這是美國第二十六屆總統 狂野騎士
founder of the national parks, and a whole bunch of other stuff.
他建造了國家公園 還有很多別的
- Have we met? - No, there's another Teddy.
- 我們認識嗎？ - 不 還有另一個泰德
We have one of you in New York.
紐約的博物館也有一個你
Really? What's he like, this other me?
真的？他長什麼樣？像我一樣？
He's pretty much the same, except with...
差不多 只是…
Except what? Say it. Except with a body?
只是什麼？只是他多了個身體？
- Yes. He has a body. - Oh, dash it, the pain!
- 是 他有身體 - 哦 見鬼 你刺激到我了
- And a horse. - Excuse me!
- 還有一匹馬 - 打斷一下
We really need someone to translate what's written on this tablet.
我們需要翻譯這塊石板上的文字
- Do you read hieroglyphics? - Yes, I do, missy.
- 你看得懂象形文字嗎？ - 是 我懂 小姐
That's a simple one.
這很簡單
Bird. Man with spear. Sideways fish. Beetle. Vase.
鳥 拿矛的人 斜過來的魚 甲蟲 花瓶
Okay, and what does that mean?
那這代表什麼？
It means, and this is just a rough translation,
我只是粗略的翻譯一下
"A man with a spear trapped a bird
一個拿矛的男人在一個花瓶
and a sideways fish in a vase."
抓住了一隻鳥和一條斜過來的魚
"And there was also a beetle."
還有一隻甲蟲
- I don't think that's it. - That's just one possible translation.
- 我想你是胡說八道 - 那只是其中一種譯法
Another possible translation is,
另一種譯法是
"You will find the combination you seek
只要能解開法老墓穴深處的秘密
"if you figure out the secret at the heart of Pharaoh's tomb."
你就能破譯密碼
Okay, and what does that mean?
好吧 那這又是什麼意思？
I don't know! What am I, the Sphinx?
不知道！你當我是誰 獅身人面像嗎？
"What's this? What's that?"
「這是什麼」 「那是什麼」
Why don't you ask New York Teddy?
你們怎麼不去問紐約那個泰德？
I'm sure he'd love to get his grabby little fingers all over that thing!
我打賭他會拿他貪婪的雙手摸遍這塊東西
Probably let his horse lick it, too!
可能還會讓他的馬舔兩下！
Mr. Daley, we should be going to the sculpture gallery.
戴利先生 我們應該去雕塑館
I think there's someone there who might have a better thought on this.
那兒有個人也許真的能幫助我們
The fellow we're looking for is just down here.
我們要找的人就在這
- Bonsoir. - Hello, young lady.
- 晚上好 - 你好 年輕人
Hey, excuse me. Could we keep moving, please?
嘿 抱歉 能快點走嗎？
We certainly could, but then we might miss a rare opportunity.
當然可以 但我不想錯過這麼好的機會
I mean, she is a Degas, Mr. Daley.
這可是德加的作品 戴利先生 （德加：法國古典印象主義畫家）
Okay, it's just I got a little buddy stuck in an hourglass,
我的小朋友被困在沙漏
I got a pitch meeting at Wal-Mart in the morning...
明天一早我還有個棘手的會議 對方是沃爾瑪…
- It would be great if we could... - He's right here.
- 請快點好嗎… - 他就在這兒
I think he'll have a thought on this.
我認為他肯定知道什麼
Mr. Thinker, we're sorry to interrupt your contemplation,
思想者先生 抱歉打斷你的沉思
but we really need to figure out the secret at the heart of Pharaoh's tomb.
可是我們真的想知道法老墓穴深處的秘密
I'm thinking. I'm thinking.
我在思考 我在思考
I'm thinking.
我在思考
- I'm thinking. - It's not happening with him.
- 我在思考 - 問他沒用
Oh, wow.
噢 哇哦
You've gotta be kidding me. Check that out!
沒開玩笑吧 看看！
- Oh, yeah. - Hey! Hey!
嘿 嘿
Buddy! Over here! This is serious.
夥計 看這兒！這很要緊！
Apparently, it's a matter of life and death.
對 生死攸關
I'll tell you what's a matter of life and death.
讓我告訴你什麼叫生死攸關
That beautiful lady over there.
看到那個美女嗎
Hey, baby! Check out the gun show going on over here!
嘿寶貝 看看我的肌肉秀
Firepower!
猛男！
He's certainly no Einstein.
看來他沒愛因斯坦那種腦子
- Biceps! Deltoids... - Yeah.
- 二頭肌！三角肌… - 對了
- Wait a minute. I saw a bunch of those. - A bunch of whats?
- 等等 我見過一堆那個 - 一堆什麼？
- Little Einsteins. - Where?
- 小愛因斯坦 - 在哪兒？
Over there, in Air and Space.
在航天航空館
I gotta get over there.
得馬上過去
What?
怎麼了？
- Nothing. - Okay. Then why are you staring at me?
- 沒什麼 - 那你這麼盯著我幹嘛？
I don't wanna miss a moment.
我不想浪費一秒鐘
All right, good, but we should get going, 'cause we...
好的 很好 不過我們得快點 因為…
- Why? - You talk too much, ace.
- 幹什麼？ - 你太囉嗦了 牛仔
I don't know why I did that, Mr. Daley.
我也不知道我為什麼吻你 戴利先生
I just feel as if I've been asleep for a long time and now, suddenly,
我只覺得我好像沉睡了很久很久
I'm awake.
突然之間 我醒了
I can explain that...
我可以解釋…
But really, I could. I really...
真的 我可以解釋…
Again, why?
又打我 為什麼？
Great, you're back.
太好了 你們又回來了
Okay. Yeah. Great.
好吧 唱得好
Love theme from Titanic. Good, but not really appropriate.
泰坦尼克的主題曲 唱得很好 謝謝你們幫倒忙
You don't let yourself enjoy things much, do you, Mr. Daley?
你就不會享受人生嗎 戴利先生？
Okay, you know what? It's not really the song choice.
聽著 不是你們選錯歌了 好嗎？
And by the way, you're a little pitchy.
還有 你們真的很煩人
Well, I thought you were amazing, and you look wonderful.
我覺得你們很棒 可愛極了
Could you just fly away, please?
飛遠點 好嗎？
And so the adventure continues.
冒險繼續
What did I tell you? Enough!
叫你們別吵了 聾了嗎？
You know, I do sort of feel like a floating butterfly.
知道嗎 我感覺自己 像只翩翩起舞的蝴蝶
You are crazier than a road lizard.
你像只臭蜥蜴
Mr. Egypt, these two here heard that we're taking over the world
埃及先生 這兩個人聽說我們要征服世界
and they want in. I don't know who they are,
他們想加入 雖然我不認識他們
but they're on exhibit here, too, apparently.
但他們也是這堛漁i品
I don't even know what they are.
他們到底是什麼東西
I'm sorry, but we're all full up in our axis of evil today. Sorry.
對不起 我們這兒壞人的名額滿了
Come on! But I'm bad! I'm bad!
別呀！我很壞 我真的很壞
Hey, I could show you how bad I am!
讓你看看我有多壞
Fear me!
怕我嗎
I'm sorry. I'm just not buying it.
對不起 我沒被嚇到
You don't seem very bad. You just seem sort of vaguely grouchy to me.
你看上去不壞 只是脾氣有點差而已
Oh, boy.
哦 上帝
What are you doing? What is that? What is this?
你在幹嘛？這是什麼？這是什麼？
What does it mean? You've lost me.
這是什麼意思？我搞不懂了
Is that you breathing? Because I can't hear myself think.
這是你呼吸的聲音嗎？ 吵得我都快不能思考了
Can I make one suggestion to you, my friend? Just simplify.
讓我給你一個建議吧 朋友 別再添亂了
There's just too much going on here.
這堣w經夠亂的了
You're evil, you're asthmatic, you're a robot...
你很邪惡 你有哮喘 你是個機器人
And what is the cape for?
還有你這斗篷是幹嘛的？
Are we going to the opera? I don't think so.
我們這兒又不是在演話劇
Sorry! Goodbye.
不好意思！再見
Attention!
有情況！
He's leaving with the tablet!
他帶著金牌逃了
Where?
哪堙H
Give me that.
讓我看
He's not trying to figure out the... He's trying to escape!
他不是在想密碼 他要逃跑！
Go. Go! All of you! Kill him! And bring me that tablet.
所有人給我追 殺了他！ 把金牌帶回來給我
Come on, people! Let's go! Without that tablet, we've nothing!
行動起來 快 金牌是我們一切的希望
Streltsy! Go!
士兵們 上！
Thought you could get away, didn't you, Larry Daley?
你逃不出我的手掌 拉瑞·戴利
Criminy, we're jimmy-jacked.
老天 我們玩完了
- Jimmy-jacked? Really? - It's the way I speak.
- 玩完了？是嗎？ - 我就是這麼說話的
Yeah, I know, but that one sounds made up, even for you.
我明白你的意思 就是聽上去有點奇怪
"Oh, no, our path has been blocked by bad people."
「不 不 我們的路被壞人堵住了」
What's the fun in that?
這麼說還有什麼意思？
The point is, we're not getting into the Air and Space right now.
問題是我們現在去不了航天航空館了
- You're right. We are jimmy-jacked. - Jimmy-jacked.
- 你說的對 我們玩完了 - 玩完了
Come on.
快
They say a good man rules this union.
他們都說那個總統是個好人
I promised Jedediah I would bring help,
我答應過傑迪戴亞我會找人幫忙
and help I will bring.
我一定會找到
Charge!
進攻！
Misjudged the distance.
低估這段距離了
Who's there?
誰？
Jupiter, protect me.
朱庇特神 求你護佑我
Remain very still.
一動不動
They can sense movement.
他們對移動很敏感
Apparently, they can also hear me talking to myself.
顯然 他們也能聽到我自言自語
I'm not a nut.
我不是堅果
No!
不要！
We should be okay in here for a while.
在這婺一會兒吧
So, how long have you guarded antiquities?
你當守衛多久了？
What? Oh, no, I don't actually work at the...
什麼？哦 其實我不在這兒工作…
I just thought with the fancy getup and all...
你的裝備看上去很齊全 所以我以為…
No, I borrowed this.
這是我借的
I mean, I was a guard back in New York, but that was a while ago.
我在紐約確實當過守衛 那是很久以前了
So why did you leave? Did you not enjoy it?
為什麼不幹了？不喜歡了嗎？
No, I loved it. I just...
不 我愛這份工作 只是…
Things sort of took off in a different direction, so...
人生往另一個方向在發展 所以…
- So what do you do now? - Well, I sort of...
- 那你現在的工作是什麼？ - 怎麼說呢…
Well, I sort of design products and sell them.
我發明產品然後銷售出去
- You're an inventor! - I am.
- 你是發明家！ - 是的
I am an inventor, yeah. I invent stuff.
我是個發明家 發明東西
Like the rocket ship?
比如火箭？
- No. - The sea plane.
- 不是 - 水上飛機？
- The dirigible? - No, not aircraft.
- 飛船？ - 不 不是飛行器
Sort of like more small-scale stuff, like...
小一點的東西 比如…
Well, the Glow-in-the-Dark Flashlight, that was mine.
比如夜光手電筒 那是我的發明
So this new job, do you like it?
那麼你喜歡這份新工作嗎？
Yeah, I like it a lot. It's exciting. It's...
是 我很喜歡 很刺激…
- What? - I'm just confused, is all.
- 怎麼了？ - 我只是有點奇怪
If you're not excited by it, why do you do it?
既然你一點都不興奮 那你為什麼幹那個？
- I am excited by it. I just said... - I know what you said, Mr. Daley,
- 我很興奮 我只是… - 別瞞我了 戴利先生
but what I see in front of me is a man who's lost his moxie.
我眼前這個人很明顯已經喪失了激情
I have not lost my...
我沒有…
I got my moxie.
我很有激情
Do you know why I became a pilot?
知道我為什麼當飛行員嗎？
- I don't, no. - For the fun of it.
- 不知道 - 因為那充滿樂趣
Why else would anyone do anything?
沒有樂趣人生還有什麼意義？
Great Gatsby!
了不起的蓋茨比！
Blast these pigeons and their incessant cooing!
走開 你們這些叫個不停的鴿子
- No! Mr. President! Sir! - All right. Time to see the state...
- 別！總統先生！ - 好了 是時候看看…
- Please don't get up! ...of this great union! I always say,
- 請別起來！ …我們偉大的聯邦了！我總是說
leave nothing for tomorrow which can be done today.
今天能幹完的事就別留到明天
Sir, if you go out there, you're gonna freak a lot of people out!
先生 你出去會嚇倒一片人的
Freak? I assure you, sir, I am no freak.
嚇人？胡說八道 我不是怪物
- No, I didn't mean you're a freak... - Come here, little one.
- 我不是說你是怪物… - 行了 小東西
In fact, if anyone is freakish, I'm afraid it's you, sir.
真要說嚇人的話 你才嚇死人了
The truth is, you are very small.
你也實在是太小了
And I mean even for a regular-sized human.
和正常人比你也算矮小的
What? Why would you even say that?
什麼？為什麼這麼說？
I must be honest.
我是實話實說
Right. Okay, Honest Abe. Of course. I'm sorry. Great.
好吧 你很誠實 你說的對
Come, now, Mr. President, put the little man down
好了 總統先生 把小傢伙放下來
and let's sit our fanny back in that throne of yours.
把你的屁股放回你的寶座上
You have a can-do attitude, and I shall do as you ask.
既然你那麼堅定 那我就照辦吧
Thank you.
謝謝
- There you go. - Thank you.
- 站好了 - 謝謝
It's that very can-do spirit that has defined this remarkable nation of ours.
堅定不移正是我們民族的偉大精神
- Interesting story. - They're coming.
- 我講個故事 - 他們追來了
One night in Gettysburg...
有一天晚上在蓋茲堡…
Mr. President, we're gonna need you to hold still now.
總統先生 請你先別動
- What? - Abraham, freeze!
- 什麼？ - 亞伯拉罕 不許動！
Freeze? I...
不許動？我…
- Thank you. - You're welcome.
- 謝謝 - 不客氣
- Come on, let's get to Air and Space. - Lf I may,
- 快 我們去航天航空館 - 允許我說一句
- you two make an adorable couple. - Oh, no, we're not...
- 你們倆真是太相配了 - 不 我們不配…
No, we're not a... I mean, we're not a...
不 你搞錯了…我們不是…
"We're not a... I mean, we're not a..."
什麼不配不配 少來了
I never lie!
我從不撒謊
The truth is, you two are adorable together.
事實就是 你們倆個在一起太相配了
Thank you. Good night.
謝謝 晚安
Farewell, lovely lady and small, little man.
再見 美麗的女士還有小個子男人
Now let's see if we can find these Einsteins of yours.
看看能不能找到你說的愛因斯坦們
One giant leap for a mannequin...
我的一小步 是人類的一大步
D.C., this is Air and Space. We are back online and fully operational.
華盛頓 這堿O航天航空館 全體啟動 全速運行
The Tuskegee Airmen are on the march once again.
黑色轟炸機又一次開始行軍
Can you stop narrating everything we're doing? Just live in the moment.
不用直播我們的每一個行動吧 享受當前的時刻吧
The Tuskegee Airmen are living in the moment!
黑色轟炸機正在享受當前的時刻
- Miss Earhart? - Yes.
- 埃爾哈特小姐 - 你好
- I wanna say thank you. - What for, Captain?
- 我想對你表示感謝 - 謝我什麼 上尉？
A lot of people didn't think we could fly, either.
很多人都認為我們成不了飛行員
Thanks for clearing the runway, ma'am.
謝謝你讓大家改變了想法
- Race you to Paris? - You're on!
- 比比誰先到巴黎？ - 接受挑戰！
No! Not now! We gotta...
不 現在不行 我們…
- It's just a quick jaunt over the pond. - No. Gotta find the Einsteins.
- 打個來回很快的 - 不行 我們是來找愛因斯坦的
Come on, we gotta go. We don't have time. Come on!
快點 我們沒時間了 快
Sorry, it's in the blood.
抱歉 看到飛機我就忍不住了
There she is, Mr. Daley.
看那兒 戴利先生
Old Bessie, the old family bus. That gal took me across the Atlantic!
老貝茜 我的老搭檔了 她帶著我飛越了大西洋
Okay. I think the Einsteins are over here, though.
好吧 不過愛因斯坦在那邊
This is Mission Control. Flight check complete.
這堿O指揮中心 起飛檢查完畢
- Where'd you go? Where'd they go? - You are clear for launch.
- 他們去哪兒了？ - 發射準備完畢
Contact!
起飛！
D.C., this is Mission Control.
華盛頓 這堿O控制中心
- No, no! No! - All systems go and green for lift-off.
- 不 不 不！ - 所有系統檢查完畢 準備發射
Roger that. We are green for lift-off.
收到 準備發射
No, we're definitely not green for any kind of lift-off!
不 絕對不能發射！
- I want a "go, no-go" for launch. - I say no-go. Let's not go.
- 到底發射不發射 - 我說不發射
Go!
發射！
- Go! - No! No go!
- 發射！ - 不！不能發射！
Torquing angles incoming.
啟動最大扭矩
Tone it down with the torque. Torque it down.
別放大扭矩 降低扭矩
De-torque. De-torque.
降低扭矩 降低扭矩
Commence ignition sequence.
開始點火倒計時
- Roger that, flight. - We have launch commit.
- 收到 - 收到發射指令
- No. No, no, no! - Ten,
- 不 不 不 不！ - 十
nine, eight, seven...
九 八 七…
- Hey, that's mine. - No, we do not have commit.
- 嘿 那是我的 - 不 沒有發射指令
Repeat. We are decommissioning the committal of the launch
重複 沒有發射指令
and it is now a negatory launch phase. We are in a no-fly, no-go phase.
發射指令無效 禁止發射 禁止起飛
That is a November-Gorgon phase of non-flying!
嚴禁任何起飛行為！
- Fine! - And we're gonna say good night.
- 好吧！ - 祝各位晚安
Thank you. Good work. Over and out.
謝謝大家 幹得好 完畢 解散
- Sorry. - Damn, that was disappointing.
- 對不起 - 見鬼 真掃興
Come on. I'll buy you a cup of coffee.
來吧 我請你喝咖啡
Hey, little space monkey.
你好 太空猴
You're Able. Okay, good. How you doing?
你叫亞伯 很好 你好嗎？
Yes, good. At ease. All right.
哦 很好 稍息 好的
You're a polite little fella, aren't you?
你非常有禮貌
Hey, you happen to know where those little Einstein bobblehead guys are?
你知道那些愛因斯坦搖頭娃娃在哪兒嗎？
Mr. Daley! I found your Einsteins.
戴利先生！我找到愛因斯坦了
Great. Hey...
太好了…
Gentlemen, we're trying to crack the combination of this tablet doodad,
先生們 我們需要你們幫我們 破譯這塊金牌的密碼
and the writing here says we'll find it
金牌上的文字告訴我們
if we figure out the secret at the heart of Pharaoh's tomb.
要破譯密碼必須破譯法老墓穴深處的秘密
That's an easy one. The answer's in the question.
很簡單 答案就蘊含在問題中
- What does that mean? - "Figure out".
- 什麼意思？ - 破譯
It's a figure! I.e., a number.
就是計算 比如 一個數字
And the Pharaoh's tomb, i.e. The pyramids.
法老的墓穴 就是金字塔
Don't you get it, kid? You're looking for the secret number
還不明白嗎 孩子？ 你們要找的就是藏在金字塔中的
at the heart of the pyramids.
那串神秘數字
Well, whistle me Dixie, the answer's pi!
哦 我懂了 答案就是圓周率！
- Pi? - 3.14159265, to be exact.
- 圓周率？ - 3.14159265 精確的來說
Yes! 3.1495265.
對！3.1495265
No, no, no, 3.14159265.
不是 是3.14159265
Yeah, okay, 3.14...
好吧 3.14…
I'm sorry, I can't tell. Is it yes or no? Cause you just...
對不起 我實在分不清 你們是在點頭還是搖頭…
I know it's hard, could you just...
我知道這對你們很難 能不能…
Don't touch the hair.
別碰頭髮
Sorry, I can't tell if it's up or...
對不起 你們的頭晃得我頭暈…
I'm a bobblehead, dummkopf,
我是個搖頭娃娃 笨蛋
and that's the way we like it. All together, now!
我們就愛搖頭晃腦 一起說
That's the way We like it
我們就愛搖頭晃腦
You know, we can't all be Einsteins, so...
知道嗎 不是人人都能當愛因斯坦…
- I can! - We are!
- 我能！ - 我們是
- He is! - Me, too!
- 他是 - 我也是
- Okay, all right. - Okay, here it is.
- 好吧 - 好 我再說一遍
- Can you slow it down a little bit? - Okay.
- 可不可以說慢一點 - 好的
- Okay. 3.14... - I've got it.
- 好的 3.14… - 我記住了
- Thank you, Mr. Einsteins. - Thank you.
- 謝謝 愛因斯坦先生 - 謝謝
All right. Now, like the brilliant and famous general that I am,
好了 作為一名偉大的將軍
I thought long and hard about what you said,
經過一番深思熟慮
and I've come up with a brand-new and improved battle plan!
我又想出了全新的升級版作戰計劃
Okay.
聽著
I will loudly announce that we are not
我會大聲宣佈
going to attack, and then...
全體不攻擊 然後…
Wait for it.
等待時機
"What's the amazing Custer about to say now? I hope he's my friend, or..."
然後大家隨便閒扯 突然
We attack!
發動攻擊！
Didn't expect your friend to run off like that, did you?
沒想到你的朋友自己逃命去了吧？
He's coming back, Ka-Ka-Ro.
他會回來的 妖怪
Sure as moon shines on a mongoose, he'll be here.
他很快就會回來救我
I would save my breath if I were you.
如果我是你就省點力氣
You don't have many left.
你離被悶死已經不遠了
We've got about 10 minutes to get over there to Jed.
還有十分鐘傑德就要被淹沒了
I think we make a good team, perhaps more than a team.
我覺得我們的合作很愉快 也許我們的關係能更進一步
Wait. Okay, wait.
等等 等一下
What's the matter? You didn't like kissing me?
怎麼了？你不喜歡吻我嗎？
No, I did. It was great. I mean,
不 我喜歡 感覺棒極了 我是說
the slapping hurt a little bit, but...
被扇耳光有那麼點疼 不過…
- So you don't like me, then. - Of course I like you. You're incredible.
- 就是說你不喜歡我 - 我當然喜歡你 你非常特別
I think you're an amazing person. You're...
你讓人無法抗拒…
It's just there are certain issues that would prevent us from...
但我們之間存在著一些障礙…
- I just... You're not... - I'm not what, Mr. Daley?
- 我只是…你不是… - 我不是什麼戴利先生？
Okay. You're made of...
好吧 你的身體是…
Made of...
身體是…
Wonderful things. You're made of good, wonderful things.
美好的東西 你的身體非常美好 非常了不起
Come on.
走吧
Gentlemen, could you buy us some time please?
男士們 能幫我們擋一會兒嗎？
It'll have to do.
看來只有這個辦法了
No! That's the first plane ever made!
不要！那是人類發明的第一架飛機
It's made out of balsa wood and paper.
它是用木板做的紙糊的
It's made out of spruce and canvas
它是用雲杉木和帆布做的
and good old-fashioned American ingenuity.
匯聚了老一代美國人的精巧工藝
Are you coming, or what?
你到底上不上來？
- Out of our way! - I don't think so.
- 讓開！ - 沒門
They're getting away!
他們逃了！
Hang on, Mr. Daley. Things are about to get interesting.
抓穩了戴利先生 這事兒越來越有意思了
A lady pilot! Preposterous!
是個女的在開！她是不是瘋了
- Think again, boys! - Oh, she's good.
- 看清楚 小子們 - 哦 她飛得真好
What? What?
怎麼了 怎麼了？
One of the wires is jammed. I'm going to have to loosen it.
一根線卡住了 我去鬆開它
- Here, take the stick! - No! I'm not gonna... No!
- 你來控制方向桿 - 不 我不要！
I know you've got moxie in you yet.
我知道你還有激情
Moxie doesn't fly planes! People who have pilots' licenses fly planes!
有激情不代表會開飛機 開飛機要飛行執照的
- Okay. - She's all yours.
- 好吧 - 交給你了
I don't want it! I don't want the stick!
不要吧！我不要這個
Don't look now, Mr. Daley, but you're flying an airplane!
別到處看戴利先生 你在駕駛飛機
Able! The doors!
亞伯！開門！
- Got it! - Pull!
- 行了！ - 下降！
Pull up!
拉升！
Yes!
好樣的！
Godspeed, Amelia Earhart!
一路順風 阿梅莉亞·埃爾哈特
Godspeed.
一路順風
Look a little nervous there, Ramen Noodle.
你有點緊張啊 蠢豬
'Cause for me, this is like a spa treatment.
我就當是做熱沙按摩
Sand baths are really rejuvenating for the skin. Exfoliates.
沙浴能幫助我恢復活力 去角質的
Giving up yet?
你放棄了吧
Not quite yet, no.
還沒有
In fact, let's see if we can't make time fly.
我可以讓時間流逝的更快些
What is that funny sound?
什麼怪聲音？
Stop!
站住！
Right there, please, Mr. Daley.
站住別動 戴利先生
Well. Well, well, well!
哇 哇…
You certainly know how to make an entrance, Mr. Daley.
你的出場很漂亮啊 戴利先生
Time to recruit some backup.
該去挖點援軍來了
I hope for your little friend's sake, here,
你朋友快淹死了
that you also figured out the combination.
但願你已經想到了密碼
- Give me Jed. - Oh, no, no, no.
- 把傑德給我 - 哦 不不不
First, give me the combination and hand over that tablet.
先給我密碼 還有金牌
I'll give you the tablet and the combination
我會把金牌和密碼給你
when you release my friends and give him back to me.
不過你先放了我的朋友們 還有把他給我
I shall release what I want to release the moment I want to release it.
我願意什麼時候放人就什麼時候放人
Great. And I'll release what I want to release
好極了 那我什麼時候願意給你
at the exact moment that I want to release it, okay?
我就什麼時候給你 怎麼樣？
Tell me the combination and give me that tablet right now
給我密碼和金牌 馬上
or I shall kill all of your friends,
否則我就殺光你的朋友
starting with the little shaggy-headed little cowman here.
首先拿這個鬍子拉楂的小牛仔開刀
I ain't shaggy-headed! Gigantor, let me take this guy!
我才不鬍子拉楂 鐵人 把這個壞蛋交給我
Don't worry, I got this handled. You don't want to give me my friends,
別擔心 我能處理 你不先放了我的朋友
then you're not gonna get your combination or your tablet.
你就別想拿到密碼和金牌
- All right, I'll tell you what. - Good.
- 好吧 你給我聽好 - 好的
They didn't call me Kahmunrah the Trustworthy for nothing.
我的外號不是什麼值得信賴的卡門拉
Here you go. They didn't call me Kahmunrah the Trustworthy!
給你 我的外號不叫值得信賴的卡門拉
They called me Kahmunrah the Bloodthirsty,
他們叫我嗜血卡門拉
who kills whoever doesn't give Kahmunrah exactly what he wants
這個卡門拉想要什麼
in the moment that he wants it, which is right now,
就要立刻得到
when I had also better get the combination and the tablet!
這個卡門拉現在要的就是金牌和密碼
- That's what they called you? - It was shorter in Egyptian.
- 你的外號很長啊 - 用埃及語會短一些
Great, I'll give you the combination after you give him back.
很好 把他給我 我就給你密碼和金牌
How dare you? If you touch that again, I shall kill you right now.
我看你再敢碰它一下 我就立刻殺了你
- Okay. - Do not touch this.
- 好吧 - 別碰它
- This is a no-touching zone! - Good. Well, then...
- 這堿O禁止觸碰區域！ - 好 好吧…
Oh, my God! I can't believe you reached across like that again!
哦上帝 我簡直不敢相信你又過界了
I can't even believe it! Oh, God, I want to kill you right...
難以置信 上帝 我真想馬上殺了你…
If you didn't know this combination, you'd be so dead right now,
要不是你知道密碼 你早就沒命了
- it would be unbelievable. - Great, but I do know the combination.
- 你會死的很難看 - 可惜我知道密碼
Don't cross this line with your hand!
不許你的手越過這條線
How dare you! If you speak again, I'm going to kill you.
膽大包天！如果你再囉嗦一句 我就殺了你
Do you understand this?
聽明白沒有？
Don't say it! Oh, God, I see you getting ready.
不許說話 上帝 我看到你嘴巴動了
- I wasn't gonna say anything. - Oh, my God, don't say anything.
- 我沒想開口說話 - 哦 上帝 不許說話
I shall murder you if you talk again.
你再說一句我就掐死你
Now give me that tablet and tell me the combination.
把金牌和密碼給我
Okay. After you give me Jed and release my friends.
可以 你先放了傑德還有我的朋友
- You did all three! - What?
- 你又犯規了 - 什麼？
You spoke and you reached your hand across!
你不僅說話了而且又把手伸過來了
Look. I can talk to you about this all night, okay?
聽著 我可以跟你繞一晚上
- How about this? - Look, just give...
- 不如這樣 - 你給我聽好…
How about I don't kill you right now, like I really, really want to,
我可以先不殺你 雖然我很想很想殺了你
and I give you precisely five seconds
我給你五秒鐘的時間
to give me that tablet and tell me the combination?
交出金牌和密碼
We already got the combination. It's pi.
我們知道密碼了 是圓周率
- 3.14159265. - No!
- 3.14159265 - 不！
- Hey. - Sorry.
- 嘿 - 對不起
So Crazy Hair here, he sang. Oh, did he sing! Like a canary.
這個怪老頭 還會唱歌 唱起來像只金絲雀
I'm sorry, Larry.
對不起 拉瑞
Enough out of you! Remember what happened last time?
你少廢話！忘了教訓了？
- That's enough. - Stupid man.
- 住手 - 蠢貨
- You okay? - Yeah, thanks.
- 你沒事吧？ - 沒事 謝謝
Must be a real bummer for you, Larry,
你肯定氣壞了吧 拉瑞
knowing that all of your valiant efforts were, in the end, for naught.
你失去了所有的籌碼
What a terrible disappointment you must be to yourself.
你肯定沮喪到不行
Do you hear that humming sound?
聽到嗡嗡聲了沒有？
Do you know what that sound is?
知道這是什麼聲音嗎？
It's rhetorical.
我在用修辭
That is the sound of the End.
那就是末日的聲音
I'm sorry, Jed.
對不起 傑德
You did your best, Gigantor.
你盡力了鐵人
Dadgum it, we almost had him, too.
見鬼 我們差點就贏了
No, I mean, I'm sorry I wasn't around the last couple of years at the museum.
不 我是說我很抱歉 前幾年我一直不在博物館
- Maybe none of this would have happened. - You don't get it, do you, Gigantor?
- 否則這一切都不會發生 - 你還不明白嗎 鐵人？
I didn't call you 'cause we needed your help.
我打給你不是我們需要幫助
Sure, we were in a little pickle,
我們確實有點小麻煩
but it wouldn't have been the first time
但這不是我第一次
I had to wrestle my way out of a root sack.
被沙緊緊地埋在下面
No, partner. I called you 'cause you needed us.
不是 夥計 我打給你是因為你需要我們
That fancy suit you've been parading around in these past couple years,
這幾年來你一直把自己隱藏在 那套光鮮的西服
that there's a hanging suit.
但在我看來 那只是一個軀殼
All gussied up, but dead inside.
如同行屍走肉
That ain't you.
那不是你
- And I'll tell you another thing. - Yeah.
- 還有件事 - 什麼
This night ain't over yet.
今夜還沒結束
This little Midnight Cowboy's got some fight left in him.
我這個小小的午夜牛仔 還有無窮的戰鬥力
Something tells me you do, too. Ho, now!
你也有 不要氣餒
Welcome to the new, extended reign of Kahmunrah,
卡門拉的統治時代到來了
Fifth King of Egypt
埃及第五代君王
and now the world!
現在將統治世界！
Horus, Ra, my warriors, come forth!
我的軍隊 前進！
Send Larry Daley and his friends to their doom!
把拉瑞·戴利和他的朋友送進地獄！
Halt!
住手！
The mighty Octavius has returned!
偉大的奧克塔維厄斯回來了！
I ride on the back of nature's most fearsome creature! I ride
我騎著全世界最最令人聞風喪膽的動物 我騎著
the squirrel!
一隻松鼠！
Forward now, my mighty steed!
前進 我的戰馬！
Whoa, girl! Easy.
悠著點 姑娘
Do you wish to surrender honorably?
你選擇繳械投降
Or must this end with the spilling of your blood?
還是血濺沙場？
This? This is your big rescue?
就這個？這就是你的援軍？
Oh, no. This is!
不 這才是！
What is that thing?
這是什麼東西？
The name is Abraham Lincoln.
我是亞伯拉罕·林肯
- And you, sir, are in a heap of trouble! - Attack it!
- 先生 你的麻煩大了 - 殺了他！
Disgusting half-pigeons!
噁心的半鳥人
No, no, no! Hello?
不 不 不！等等！
Adios, bird brains!
滾吧 鳥人
Wait, wait, wait. No, no!
等等 等等 別！
Goodbye, strange birdmen.
再見了 鳥人
Do not return to the Underworld!
別回地下世界！
Yes, yes, do go back into the Underworld!
對 對 回你們老家去吧！
Thank you for coming! Good night!
謝謝光臨 晚安！
No, no!
不 不！
Oh, this is awkward.
真是尷尬
It appears my work here is done.
這兒好像沒我什麼事了
Just remember, son, a house divided against itself cannot stand.
記住我的話孩子 家庭不睦 萬事不興
Farewell.
再見
- What now? - You know, I'm not quite sure.
- 現在怎麼辦？ - 我也不知道怎麼辦
I suppose we should probably start by watching him die.
我要看到他死
Streltsy! Make him dead!
士兵 殺了他
Now what?
又怎麼了？
We are not going to attack right
我們現在不準備
now!
攻擊！
Get them!
給我上！
Fear not, Larry! I will help Jedediah!
別擔心 拉瑞 我去救傑迪戴亞！
You come at them from behind!
你去後面包抄
- Hey, what's going on? - I'm hiding.
- 嘿 你在幹嘛？ - 我在找地方隱蔽
Hiding? What are you doing? Come on, we need you.
隱蔽？你在搞什麼！ 快 我們這兒需要你
- I'm a failure. - No, you're not.
- 我是個失敗者 - 不 你不是
Did you foolishly lead 208 Americans to their deaths
你試過愚蠢地帶領208個美國人打仗 最後全軍覆滅
at the Battle of Little Bighorn?
就在小比格霍恩河戰役？
- No. - No? Not good. Not good at all.
- 沒有 - 沒有 那感覺不好 真的不好
- That's not good. - Sure, I talk a good game,
- 感覺不好 - 當然 我也就能動動嘴皮子
but the truth of the matter is, I don't deserve these stars.
干真的不行 我不配肩膀上的軍銜
I will always be famous for my biggest failure.
人們永遠只記得我的失敗
Hey.
嘿
The past is the past, okay?
過去的就讓它過去 好嗎？
Right now, this moment, this night,
現在 當下 就在今夜
this is what you're gonna be remembered for.
這場戰役將永垂青史
This is your last stand.
這是你的最後一戰
- They need a leader. - Yeah, they need a leader.
- 我們需要一位領袖 - 是啊 他們需要領袖
Yeah? You want to be their leader, huh?
是嗎？你願意去領導他們嗎？
- Yeah, I do. - Let's do this!
- 是 我願意 - 那就站起來！
- All right? - Yeah.
- 怎麼樣？ - 好
Let's go!
我們走！
Not good!
太糟了！
Larry!
拉瑞！
Hey, Able!
嘿 亞伯！
I want to help!
我需要幫助
Oh, great.
哦 好的
Who are you? This is my museum!
你是誰？這是我的博物館
Well, he's my human. Back off!
他是我的人 你走開
You need all the help you can get, Jungle-Dweller!
你儘管拉人 你這個野蠻人
Get over yourself space snob!
少廢話 你這個太空佬
Guys! Hey, guys!
夥計們！嘿 夥計們！
This is not the time to get into this, all right?
現在不是爭這些的時候 好嗎？
Dexter, you know better.
德克斯特 你知道規矩
All right? That's what happens when you do that!
好嗎 再胡鬧就請你們吃耳光
You get that.
給你一耳光
Stop! Just stop! Stop!
住手 都給我住手！
Now, listen. You're both proud capuchin!
聽著 你們都是高貴的僧帽猴
You need to concentrate on slapping the enemy!
應該一直對外 抗擊外敵
Keep it together, all right?
團結起來 行嗎？
Come on, let's go! Let's do it!
快 衝上去 給我打
- Jedediah! They need us! - I ain't gonna make it!
- 傑迪戴亞 大家需要我們 - 我恐怕不行了
Afraid this cowboy's been to his last hoedown.
恐怕我的日子到頭了
Octavius, remember me as I was, wild, and free, and...
奧克塔維厄斯 記住我的精神 自由 狂野…
- No need for final words. - I'm not finished yet.
- 還不是說遺言的時候 - 我還沒說完
I want to get to the story of our relationship,
我還想回憶一下我們的那段事
the evolution from enemy to friends.
我們是怎麼從敵人變成朋友的
- No! - It'll make you cry!
- 不要！ - 你想哭就哭吧！
No! Because you are going to live!
不！因為你還死不了！
- Let's go to work. - Have a sword.
- 該我們上場了 - 拿著劍
Sword!
拿劍來！
Incoming!
上面！
That smarts.
好疼
You smack, you kick! You smack, you kick!
你打 你踢！ 你打 你踢！
You smack, you kick! Teamwork, fellas! Wunderbar!
你打 你踢！ 幹得漂亮 夥計們！
How you doing, fellas?
你們好啊 夥計們！
- Are you all right? - Never better.
- 你還好嗎？ - 再好沒有
Listen, when I give you the signal, I want you to open the gate.
聽著 一看到我的信號就立刻打開門
- I take it you have a plan. - I'm gonna divide the house.
- 看來你成竹在胸 - 我要去搞點小破壞
The tablet! Now!
金牌給我 馬上！
Okay, sure, you can have it.
好的 當然 我會給你
Just tell me who the boss is and I'll give it to you.
告訴我你們誰是頭 我就給他
Or should I give it to Kahmunrah? He's your master, right?
要不我給卡門拉? 他看上去是你們頭 不是嗎？
Nyet! He is not our master!
放屁 他才不是什麼頭
Really? 'Cause he acts like he is.
是嗎？我看一直是他在說了算
But fine, just tell me who the boss is and you can have it.
算了 你就告訴我你們誰是頭 我就給誰
Hey! That'd be me.
我是頭！
This man is a peasant! I am the only one here of noble birth!
他是個農民 我才是這堸艉@有貴族血統的人
Really? 'Cause he's got more medals and a bigger hat, but...
是嗎？可是他看上去有更多勳章 帽子也更大 不過…
- Thank you. - You might got a lot of medals,
- 謝謝 - 你確實有很多勳章
but you put one of your little child hands on that tablet again,
但是你要再敢用你的小手碰一下金牌
it'll be the last thing them tiny little mitts of yours ever touch.
我就要你好看
Why would you touch little Nippy?
你幹嘛要傷害小拿拿？
I can handle this, okay?
我能自己解決 好嗎？
You can handle nothing! You can barely speak, you fool!
你什麼也解決不了 你連話都說不清楚 蠢貨！
You know what? No problem. I'll give it to you. You see that?
沒問題 你要是嗎 我給你
Oh, you're a spunky little fella!
你這個小雜種
Very clever, Mr. Daley, getting them to fight amongst themselves.
幹得漂亮 戴利先生 讓他們自相殘殺
Yeah. I can't really take credit. It was Abraham Lincoln's idea.
對 我不敢邀功 這主意是亞伯拉罕·林肯想出來的
You know, a house divided can't...
家庭不睦 萬事不興…
- Doesn't do well. - Yes, well,
- 還做得不夠 - 沒錯
you should have saved yourself when you had the chance,
剛才你就應該自己逃命的
because now I shall have the tremendous pleasure
可惜你又落在了我手
of killing you myself!
我現在最想做的事就是親手殺了你
What are you?
你到底是什麼人？
I'm the night guard.
我是個守衛
No!
不！
Victory is ours!
勝利屬於我們！
Yeah!
耶！
That's what I'm talking about!
我說什麼來著！
I'd say somebody found his moxie.
我看到有個人終於找回他的激情了
The Battle of the Smithsonian.
史密森尼戰役
Perhaps the greatest battle the world will never know.
將是一場永遠不為人知的偉大戰役
We'll know.
我們都見證了
Yeah.
是啊
Oh, man, I got an hour till sunrise. I got to get you guys back.
噢 老天 還有一個小時就天亮了 我得把你們都弄回去
In case you forgot, Gigantor, they don't want us there anymore.
我不得不提醒你鐵人 那兒的人不再需要我們了
Well, I do.
不 我需要
Hey, think you could hook us up with a ride?
嘿 可以載我們一程嗎？
My pleasure, of course.
當然 我很榮幸
Hang on a second. One last thing I got to take care of.
稍等 我還有件事要辦
Come on, boy! Come on, come on!
快 孩子！來啊
Get in there!
跳進去！
Feels good, right?
很舒服吧？
You're welcome! Just get back inside by sunrise, okay?
別客氣！ 記得天亮前一定要回去！
These are promising days, indeed.
這真是一個光明的時代
All right. Hey, come on, guys.
好了 夥計們 動作快
Remember, stay with your buddy, all right?
記得和同伴呆在一起
Good, good.
好 好
Well, you're back where you belong.
好了 你回到該回的地方了
Yeah. Think so.
我想是的
I guess I should be going.
我想我該走了
Hey, Amelia.
阿梅莉亞
That thing that I was trying to tell you about earlier...
早些時候我想告訴你的那件事…
There's not really an easy way to put this,
我真的很難說出口
- but, in the morning... - I know what's coming, Mr. Daley.
- 但是 一旦天亮… - 我知道會發生什麼 戴利先生
I've always known.
我一直知道
But it doesn't matter.
不過沒關係
You've given me the adventure of a lifetime in one night.
在一夜之間 你給了我一生都未曾體驗過的冒險經歷
And I have a feeling it's going to be a beautiful sunrise.
我覺得今天的日出一定特別美麗
Have fun.
要快樂
Thanks.
謝謝
I don't know about you fellas, but this old cowboy just got to second base.
不知道你怎麼想 夥計 可這個老牛仔才攻到二壘
- There she goes. - Straight towards...
- 她飛走了 - 頭也不回…
Canada.
加拿大
She's heading to Canada.
她在往加拿大飛
No, now she course-corrected.
航向正確
Here, head on downstairs, guys.
去地下室 夥計們
- All righty. - Good night, Larry.
- 好的 - 晚上好 拉瑞
Hey, boy, how's it going?
孩子 你好嗎？
Lawrence! Bless you for bringing them back.
勞倫斯！謝謝你把他們都帶回來
And might I say, a hearty well-done is in order.
你幹的真是太漂亮了
And may I also point out, they cannot hide in the basement forever.
可是他們不能在地下室躲一輩子
Yeah. No, I think I got that figured out.
不 我已經想到辦法了
- Really? - Yeah.
- 真的 - 對
Sun come, dum-dum.
日出 笨瓜
Our moai friend is right. The dawn will soon be upon us.
我們摩艾朋友說的對 日出即將來臨
Hey, Teddy.
泰德
Remember the other night you were saying something
還記得那天晚上你和我說的嗎
about the key to happiness?
你說幸福的關鍵是
- Did I? - You said, "The key to happiness is..."
- 我說了嗎？ - 你說：「幸福的關鍵是…」
And then the sun came up and you froze.
然後太陽出來你就凍住了
- I think I got it figured out. - Yes?
- 我想我知道答案了 - 是嗎？
It's doing what you love, isn't it? With people you love.
就是做你愛做的事 對不對 和你愛的人在一起
Actually, I was going to say "physical exercise",
其實 我想說的是「鍛煉身體」
but the love thing's good, too.
不過你說的也不錯
- Lawrence! - Yeah.
- 勞倫斯 - 什麼
Welcome home, son.
歡迎回家 孩子
Thanks.
謝謝
Well, folks, the wait is over. After two months of renovation,
朋友們 漫長的等待終於結束 經過了2個月的整修
tonight, The Museum of Natural History reopens its doors to the public.
今夜 自然歷史博物館將重新對公眾開放
As you can see, New Yorkers are flooding in,
如你所見 紐約市民正迫不及待的涌進博物館
eager to see just what changes are in store.
想親身體驗博物館
With its new, extended night hours,
新推出的夜遊項目
we're told the museum will be more lively than ever.
據說夜間博物館的展品 比以往更加栩栩如生
I see the uniform still fits after these long, long years.
都過了這麼久了 這身制服倒還合身
Yeah, yeah. Really hasn't been that long, but...
是啊 不過也沒過多久嘛…
So, to what do we owe this "triumphant" return?
那麼 這場喜慶回歸的代價是什麼？
Not cut out for the "corporate" jungle after all. Got fired.
還是適應不了商場 被裁了？
No, actually, I sold my company.
實際上 我把公司賣了
The world doth move in mysterious ways.
這個世界的變化令人難以捉摸
One day, we've got to get rid of everything old,
前一天我們還在清理所有老展品
the next, a rich, anonymous donor gives a huge endowment.
後一天 一個富有的無名氏突然捐助了博物館一大筆資金
With a proviso: Everything stays the same. So...
條件就是 保持所有老展品不變…
- Well, not exactly the same, obviously. - No.
- 很明顯 也不是一點沒變 - 不是
Bully, lads and ladies, the name is Theodore Roosevelt,
注意 女士們先生們 我是西奧多·羅斯福
naturalist, Rough Rider and twenty-sixth President of these great United States.
一個自然主義者 又名狂野騎士 美國的第26任總統
Come along, lad. The hunt is afoot. Lawrence.
跟上 孩子 冒險開始 勞倫斯
Hey, you dum-dums bring me gum-gum?
嘿 你們這些笨瓜給我帶口香糖嗎？
My parents gave me this tablet some 3,000 years ago,
大約3000年前 我父母給了我這塊金牌
entrusting me with one of my people's most prized possessions.
這是埃及人民最至高無上的寶物
- Does it do anything? - Do anything?
- 它有什麼用？ - 什麼用？
Yeah. What's the point if it doesn't do anything?
對 如果沒用的話要它來幹嘛？
Tell 'em
告訴他們
Actually, it has a magical power
實際上 它是一塊復活金牌
that brings all the exhibits to life.
可以讓這堛漁i覽品都活過來
No, really, what's it do?
好了 別開玩笑 它到底有什麼用？
Nothing. It's just for decoration.
沒用 只是裝飾品
I knew it.
我就知道
This place is lame. This thing doesn't even look real.
這媊窸z了 這個恐龍看上去一點都不真實
Seriously, dude, these animatronics suck.
沒錯 老兄 這堛犒q動技術太落後了
- Mammoth? - Yeah.
- 猛?象？ - 是啊
Extinct!
絕種了！
- Today's technology is beyond me. - I know. It's so lifelike.
- 我已經跟不上科技發展了 - 是啊 做的像真的一樣
- Yeah, yeah, yeah. - Something else.
- 是的 是的 - 問你件事
You'll stick around a bit longer this time,
這次你打算做久一點
or you gonna run away again when you get something better?
還是像上次一樣幹了一半 又去幹別的？
- I'm gonna stay. - Stay, for a long time.
- 我會呆下去 - 一直呆下去？
- Yeah. - Yeah.
- 是的 - 是的
Good. 'Cause, as night guards go, you're...
很好 作為一個守衛 你…
- What? - The best.
- 什麼？ - 是最棒的
Excuse me.
我沒聽清
You, the toddler! Don't hug the displays.
你 小孩！不可以抱展覽品
I'm sorry. Hi.
打擾了 你好
I don't mean to stare. I just...
請原諒我的冒昧 我只是…
You look a lot like somebody I know, and...
你和我認識的一個人長得很像…
I get that a lot.
很多人都這麼說
- Do you? - Yeah. I guess I have that kind of face.
- 是嗎？ - 對 可能是我長了一張大眾臉吧
- Familiar. - Yeah.
- 大眾臉 - 是啊
You're not by any chance related to Amelia Earhart, are you?
你不會碰巧和阿梅莉亞·埃爾哈特 有什麼親屬關係吧
- No. - No.
- 沒有 - 沒有
- No, I don't think so. - Of course you're not.
- 我想沒有 - 當然沒有
I mean, I don't know. Maybe I'm...
我是說 我不知道 也許我…
I just had to ask. I'm sorry.
我只是忍不住想問 對不起
She was that woman who flew across the Pacific.
她是那個第一個飛越太平洋的女性吧
- The Atlantic. - Atlantic. Of course.
- 大西洋 - 對 是大西洋
First woman to fly across the Atlantic, and she received the Flying Cross,
第一個飛越大西洋的女性 她還獲得過飛行十字勳章
first woman to do that.
女性當中也是第一個
- That's very cool. - Yeah, she was cool.
- 真酷啊 - 對 她真的很酷
Hey, you know what you should check out is the the Hall of Miniatures.
你應該去微縮模型館看看
Could you take me there? I'm always getting lost.
你能給我帶路嗎？我總是迷路
Yeah, I know. Sure. Yeah, I'll show you. Come on.
好的 當然 我來帶路 來吧
Thank you.
謝謝
- I'm Larry Daley. - Tess.
- 我叫拉瑞·戴利 - 苔絲
- Joseph, time for dinner! - One second, Ma!
- 約瑟夫 吃晚飯了！ - 馬上來 媽媽
Joey Motorola, you get down here for supper right now!
喬伊·摩托羅拉 馬上給我下樓吃飯！
I said one second, Ma! I really think I'm on to something here!
我說了馬上來 媽 我正在研究一個很重要的東西